 DEV AR SHUMWAY Blanding, Utah Tape No. 7An interview by Kathy Biel July 28, 1970American West Center University of Utah Uranium History Series
 Table of ContentsNavajos as Miners.Navajos and Whites Working Dependability of Navajos Superstitions of Navajos.1 Together • • • 10 11 . 14 Future of Mining on the Reservation • • • 17
 THIS IS AN INTERVIEW WITH DEVAR SHUMWAY FOR THE UNIVERSITY OF UTAH AND CALIFORNIA STATE COLLEGE AT FULLERTON, URANIUM INDUSTRY ORAL HISTORY PROJECT. MR. SHUMWAY IS A MINE OWNER AND A PROSPECTOR.THE INTERVIEW TOOK PLACE AT MR. SHUMWAY'S MOTHER ' S HOME IN BLANDING, UTAH ON JULY 28, 1970 AT SEVEN IN THE MORNING. THE INTERVIEWER IS KATHY KIEL.KB: Okay, the area I want to go into lies about here in Navajo miners and employers, and this is where I want to ask the questions about. Just what kind of employees do they make and why did you hire them? How many Navajo employees would you say you had right now?DS: We've only got fourteen working for us right now, but we have had probably in the neighborhood of seventy of them at one time. My opinion of the Navajo people is that unlike what most people think, they are an intelligent people and they're real good miners. I don't know how come I didn't start using Navajos before I did. I probably didn't realize that they were such good hands. They've b.een, with the exception of maybe in leadership capacity, why, they've been the best hands that I've ever had. As far as beingminers, they're real good workers; they're good to put in their full eight hours, and they're not afraid to do anything. I mean some White men don't like to fool around with a shoveL 'They'.11 use their loaders. after it isn't practical anymore to use loaders, and Navajos will go ahead and clean up real good with a shovel for the next ground. This is quite important, especially at times
 SHUMWAYP AGE 2when you're shooting waste one time and ore the next, why, you need to clean all the waste b.efore you shoot your ore in. They make a cleaner ore. With the exception of leadership capacity, why, they are real good hands.. Even then, why, as just as shifter or something this. way, a hoss- of their own people, why, you--you occasionallyrun across a miner that is real good this way. We've had severalof them. Do you want me to mention names on this? KB: Yes, I do.DS: There was a Harrison Benally that was one of the first Navajos with some leadership ability that we had working for us. He was--he had quite a lot of experience in mines and was a good miner, understoodmost anything that he needed to know as far as the production of ore, or doing the exploration where it did work, and so forth. He understood the equipment, and the men respected him, or feared him, or something, I don't know which. We had several of them after that. There was a Tom Lee that we had who was a really good hand and had plenty of leadership ahility among his own people and used good judgment in most cases. I rememb.er one instance where up at Crested Butte, during the hard rock competition up there, why, he won in almost every category--the drilling, and there was. lots of--theywas drawing from hundreds. of White men up there that could compete in this; it was the Fourth of JulyQ And these White men just flat
 SHUMWAY PAGE 3learned then that he out-hand-mucked them, he out-mucked them the 12B Unco Mucker, and he out-drilled them. I forgot what all the competition was, but he had to set up his equipment and then go ahead and--like if he was going to drill a hole, and they were giving twenty minutes to drill into a slab of rock there, and he's the only miner that drilled through ·it. He had, I think, about eighteen seconds left of his twenty minutes after he had drilled all the way through it. It was a real hard material. But thesepeople, I've noticed a lot of times would even have White men trying to out do them. The Navajo would be working with several Navajos. There was a Woody Dee, and Carl Thomas, and Billy John--no, it was John Nesbogay, and several other Navajos that we have had. Theyjust consistantly on a contract of some kind would make around thirty ton of ore a day, and we'd just tell some White men, "Let's see ifyou can muck more than this guy does." We wouldn't even tell tell the Navajo that he was in competition. And just on this contract, why, he'd come up with three or four more tons during the day thanthe White man would who was just a-swearin', and a-blowin', anda-goin' and trying to heat him. But like I said, I do have a lotof respect for them as far as good honest workers and, of course, they,like most anybody else, will do more on contract than they do just Ifor daily pay. B.ut I don't know of hardly any time that I ever
 SHUMWAYPAGE 4caught a Navajo just plain goofing off, just not doing anything. They're always busy doing something for the full eight hours, and this is something in this day and age to have people that do putin eight hours work for eight hours pay. So from the standpointof their intelligence, the standpoint of their being good workers, and the standpoint of them being a proud people, I'm sure that there's a lot of them that know that they could come over here and draw welfare checks that would amount to just about as much aswhat they're getting working for wages. But they'd rather go ahead and work for wages than to draw their welfare check wherever it's possib.le, or at least a lot of them would. Ones that are presentlyworking, why, I'm real sure that they could do just about as well financially doing nothing as they could working for a living. And this, too, is to their credit. Like I say, they're a proud people. They're not a thrifty people in anyway, but--in fact, I don't believe that I've known a Navajo that was--that had the net worth of asmuch as ten thousand dollars. They'll usually have what we call a Navajo Cadillac, which is a new Chevrolet pickup or a new Ford pickup s,o they can head back for the reservation for their four day weekend. We usually work from mayhe eleven on and three off, or ten on and four off, or something this way. And just about without exception, why, they head hack to home ground when they get their paycheck and come hack without any of it. Ususally, they've got credit at some
 SHUMWAY PAGE 5store or something this: way, and they just live from month to month. I've never known any of them with a bank account either. I'm sure some of them do have. When you get among the ones on the reservation, a few of them trus:t their money in a bank, but most of them, if they've got any left over, and they're saving any for the next weekor something this way, they'd rather trust their money with the traders or somebody than with the bank. But occasionally, you do find one that mayb.e has got a few dollars left over for grocerymoney until their next payday. It seems that not matter how much they make, why, we've had men on contract that have made, oh, well over a thousand dollars a month, but it doesn't make a bit of diff- erence to them. It just mayb.e takes them one or two days longerto spend it than it does the ones that have a regular paycheck,or so much per hour for eight hours a day, and usually one or two days overtime in a payday. But on contract, why, I've had men make, oh, fifteen or eighteen hundred dollars a month for several months in a row, and yet they don't have any more left over when they comeback from the reservation than the ones who were working for wages. So I wouldn't say they were a thrifty people in any way. At least, they never plan to see a millionaire in the crowd or anything thisway. Yet it's possible that it's just the ones I know--the miners are the only ones that I know. It's possible that there are such
 SHUMWAY PAGE 6things as Navajo millionaires, but it's certainly doubtful.KB: I think it was Dick Randall who told me he had a bank account inShiprock, and he's very proud of that. DS: Oh., has he?KB: I don't know if it was true or not, b.ut he claims he does. Are most of your miners then on contracts?DS: No, not now, there's none of them on contract. When I was operating pers.onally, why, I usually had some contract figured up for them because it's not only better for them, but it's also better forme. They make a hetter grade of ore and b.etter production and so forth.on a contract for a little more money than they do working for wages. B.ut the company policy of Homestead Minerals right now isto just have them on wages, so there's nothing I can do ab.out it without going through Denver and this is--I'd rather give theman extra overtime day or s.omething that I can cover up for than to try to put them on contract because the head officials in Homestead Minerals don't understarid this, and don't hardly agree with the fact that I can get more out of them in that route ·than I could in some other way. Just company policy.KB.: What's just about the highest you do pay the men, then, on an hourly wage?DS; Uh, $3.75 is the most that anyone's getting per hour on hourly wage.
 SHUMWAY P AGE 7KB: What job would this be?DS: Uh, usually a real good man that is in leadership with leadershipahility who can work ten men effectively, efficiently. Th.ere'sno need of raising a man's pay to over three dollars, or something like that, unless--unless he does have some ability other thanb.eing just a good miner because you can get all the miners you wantat three dollars and down to two and a half or something this way.We have had the policy in the past of starting men at two and a quarter, and if they work for the first two weeks, why, then they--I mean work the first pay period, why, then they're raised to two sixty. But if it's just a tramp miner comes along that's just working for two or three days· wages, why, it isn't even worth it to start them. So we usually start them--tell them it'll just b.e two and a quarter for the first two weeks, and then he'll be raised to twosixty. Then if he's willing to go that route, why, he's one thatwill stay a while longer. You get them to stay longer by doing itthis. way.KB: Uh, do you have--do you use any of the big equipment in these minesfor Homestead Minerals?DS: Uh, most of it is--no, they're not what you'd call big equipmentunderground. There's front end loaders, and so forth. Some of it's John Deer 20/10 or John Deer 450's and these International
 SHUMWAY PAGE 8TD3 parties that are little loaders and then Bob.cats.. Some air equipment like Unco Muckers and then, of course, there's diesel travelers that move a string of cars in and out, or else shadow cars. Most of our shadow cars are Gettman. There's four of them that w:e've got that are three ton buggies and haul about three tons at a trip, and then we've got about fifteen that just hauls one ton at a trip that we put up in the raises, and stops, and different places where we don't have track. Where there isn't track already laid, why, we usually put in trackless equipment that tribes the stuff out. Usually a one wheel in front, or whichever you want to call it; front or b.ack--they go either direction with ab.out the same efficiency. Going up hill, why, you have the load so thatmost of it is on the back wheels or drive wheels. But you turn around and go up backwards, and the driver is going backwardswhen you're going up the hill like that to get most of the traction on the drive wheels. This is about the amount of power equipmentw.e have, hut it isn't large equipment compared to, oh, some of these excavation equipment on highways--building highways or strip mining. In the mines that you strip, of course, you'd have some large equipment. But due to the thickness of the origin of the Ura VanMineral B.elt, why, you try and keep equipment that doesn't require too much headroom to dump, and to operate underground, to turn
 SHUMWAY P AGE 9around, and so forth. You want to keep it down so that you don'thave to shoot too much_was.te and make headroom for it, and so forth. KB: Uh, do the Indians run all the equipment?DS: Y es.KB.: They run it, even the largest equipment?DS: Yes. We don't have any equipment hut what at least some of thesefellows can run. They're experienced on some of this when theycome with.us, others learn. Now this Henry Black that you inter- viewed the other day, why, he started over across the canyon around ten years ago, or something like that on Bobcats. He's just about as efficient on a Bobcat--one of these little Melrow motors, that's a Deutsch diesel motor, and Melrow loading equipment that he started on over there. He can run any of the equipment, starts and operates any of the equipment that we've got around there. And if there's any of it he doesn't already know how to operate, why, he'll take time sometime and learn how to· run it. But these people have quitea desire, it seems like, to learn different things, which is to their credit also. They're not afraid to run any equipment. Even on their own time sometimes, why, they'll come and mess around with it just to learn to run it. If somebody won't let them run itduring the working hours, why, they'd kind of like to just learn how to run it and will even go to school and so forth to learn to
 SHUMWAY P AGE 1 0run some of this equipment that they don't already know-. So when they go looking for a jofi next time, why, they can name just about anything they can do--ahout anything that a miner operator might require and might desire that they he ab.le to run. And a lot of these Navajos can run more equipment than most any White man you'll find. In fact, I don't have a man today but what I would say was quite a lot better operator on some equipment or in some areas than I am. In fact, I've been away from it for so long, about all Ineed to know is how to negotiate contracts, and leases, and a few things this. way. In my capacity, especially you should maybe know how to choose good men, or at least better men than I am at doing this work. I always felt that if you kept good men around you,w:hy, you didn't have to know very much of anything yourself.KR: Do you every have White miners working together with your Indianminers.? CS: Yes.KR: In the same mines?CS: Yes.KR: How does that work out?CS: Uh, sometimes, why, the White men get to thinking they're a littlehetter than the Navajos, and all you have to do is try to get them to prove it, and they fail miserably, usually. This is one reason, as I was telling you, quite often I'd have some men trying to outdo a Navajo. He'd get to thinking that he was a lot better hand, and
 SHUMWAY PAGE 1 1so forth, than the Navajo, and I'd just tell him to go and try hand- mucking with hi.ID. a day, or something this way. And this'll soon givethem a little more res.oect for these people. They know they're not even notified that they're in competition, and yet the White man generally finds that he can't compete with him. But most of theminers that work with these people, they respect them to the extent that they get along with. them real good. They, mayb.e, don't want to party with them, and they maybe don't want to associate with them after working hours, and so forth, but as far as working with them, why--why-, they realize they're on the same level that theyare, and they work with them, without exception--without very manyexceptions, at least, they get along real good that way.KR: Well, there seems to b.e a difference of opinion between differentemployers of Navajos in their mines. Some I've talked to have said that you can never depend on them. And they talk ab.out "Navajotime," and also about stealing. How do you account for this difference of opinion b.etween employers?DS: Navajos will steal different things than White people do. They'd never steal a jackhammer, and they never steal things for resale. They'll s.teal gasoline, and they'll steal oil, and they'll steal Prestone and some of the things they're going to use in their ownvehicle. B.ut you find that a lot of the White people that you have
 SHUMWAY PAGE 12working for you will steal b.ig things for resale. Some of them don't--1 mean most of them don't, hut a Navajo admittedly and almost without exception will steal gasoline to go back to the reservation on, and I've known of this all along, but they usually only steal ten gallons. And they usually don't steal five gallon cans and haul enough down there so they'll have enough to get back on, and so forth. Whenever I find that they're doing this, why,I notify them that th.is is going a little too far. But I always figured it was just part of their salary, or part of their wages, or s.omething to steal ten gallons of gas when they leave. Andmayhe a little bit to run hack and forth to the mines then, and mayb.e a few things this way. Yeah, there's no question hut what they will do this, and when they're talking ab.out "Navajo time,"why, I know exactly what they're talking about. It's very seldom that you've got a good crew back on Monday morning. They staya little longer on the reservation than they were supposed to, and they're not as dependahle as the white men, but a few of them are quite dependab.le. You can come up with a fair crew if you have called th.em pretty good to where y-ou do come up with a few of them to go to work the next morning. I don't know how many people you'vetalked to that figured that they're not as good workers as White people. Is thi s one area that you're talking about that some people
 SHUMWAY P A G E 1 3figure that they're just not as efficient as miner as the Whitepeople?KB: Uh, it doesn't seem to be a matter of efficiency. It's dependability. DS: Dependability.KB.: And also the stealing. Some of them say that they really dori ' t : haveany ambition. They don't want to take on leadership jobs, forinstance. But you seem to feel that there are some who do though. DS: Some of them do. They're rare. There's--most of them are notcapable of being a leader amongst their own people. In fact, it's very seldom that you come up with one that they show respect to.And they have a fear of their own people to the extent where justa lot of these men, why, they have troubles that some of the other fellows will just tease them about, or give them a bad time, and they'll get drunk and run away from camp, and things this way. It's kind of iaexcusahle, as near as I can tell, for a person to be that afraid of somebody else. Why they don't get a baseball bat andteach these people something, I don't hardly understand. But Indians are to quite an extent this way, and I don't know that it bears up entirely my theory on this, hut they give each other kind of a bad time. They'll bully one another, and so forth, but it isn't necess-arily the hully that's got the leadership ability. I can't hardly put my finger on just what it is that these people--hut you'll find
 SHUMWAY PAGE 14one man in maybe twenty-five, or s.omething like that, that these people will respect, who they don't try to bully. This man don't bully them, hut he'll come up with leadership ahility prob.ably asthe son of the man who's got lots of sheep, or something this way.And they know this; they know·his dad is respected and so forth.And for some reason, why-, this man they· show respect to, and thisis the man you're looking for to put in a job of responsibility.And it's rare that you come up with somebody like this, b.ut--andit isn't necessarily that the man can outdo some of the others working every time. But like I say, I can't tell you exactly what it is,or how it comes about, or anything, but I just try to recognize it in men that we have, and try and raise them, keep them going up the ladder as far as they're capab.le of going. I'm not even sure I'm explaining this the way somebody else could understand it, but it's. there, and it shows up once in a while, and you try to take advantage of it.KB.: What ahout superstition, do you run across any superstitions theyhave ahout mines. or the kind of work .they do? Does this ever prohibit work heing done?DS: No. I don't think as far as working is concerned that they have any supers.titions about that. But--oh, like mokey-digging, or something, or something this way, why, you can't get--I've never found any of
 SHUMWAY P AGE 1 5of them that--there was a George Tat one time that told me he was a good hand. He worked for us for several years, and he told me that if I'd come down to Shiprock with him, there was quite a number of ruins that we could go digging in. He was working for the government and figured that he had--that he could keep the law away fn0m us,and so forth. But b.y·the time I got down there, why, he said that the law had changed to where he was scared to go and do this. Butmost of them, it's just plain through superstition that they figμre, and some of these who I'm talking about that have been in leadership capacity, why, they will tell you where these ruins are. They'llmayb.e sit somewhere back on a hill and watch you, but they wouldn't any more dig _up under thes-e dead people than anything. They can't figure out how come I'm still alive. You know this Harris Banelly told 1ne--he says. that he went and dug up one of these people and so he'd have to go to the medicine man for three days and three nights or die. He just figured--there's no question in his mind but whatif he dug up one of these people and took the dishes from them, why, he'd die, or els·e he'd have to spend three days and three nights with the medicine man. And they are real superstitious, all of them, in some areas. I think that's almost without exception. They don't-- they don't get enough education so that they are not afraid to go anddo s.ome of the things they have been taught for generations not to do.
 SHUMWAY PAGE 16KB.: We were talking about supers.titians. Are there any others you can think of besides.mochey-digging? What ab.out their fear of death? Don't they have a stronger fear of death then the White man?DS: Well, I don't know. I don't see any evidence of it.KK: Oh, you don't?DS: If they do have, why--oh, they have a different way of combattingdeath. They comb.at it in kind of a superstitious way, or a way that their people have done it for years. But they still use the medicineman when the modern doctors fail, or maybe even to some extent they use the medicine man when a doctor is available, oh, in preference to a medical doctor. But their death rate is real high, especially amongst the young. They lose a lot of their babies, and lots of their younger children. I don't see any evidence of there beingmore of the fear of death amongst them than there is among Whitepeople. I think that there's the fear of death amongst everybody,as far as that goes. But, I don't know that I could consider itany stronger among them than it is among Whites, or Negroes, or anybody else.KB.: How· do you think they feel about mining off the reservation? Do you think most of them would prefer mining in the mines that are on the reservation if they were still going?DS: Well, I've talked to a few of them about this, but they have minimum wage--or maximum wage scales on the reservation that doesn't allow
 SHUMWAY PAGE 17them to make near the money that they can make off of the reservation. KB.: Is this in the mines?DS: Yes, and we're talking about mining the mines they have. Here awhile back, it was about a dollar and eighty cents that was the maximum that they could make per hour on the reservation. Now thisis something that I understand is set by the Tribal Council. They only allow their people to make that amount because they're afraid all of them would quit · their road jobs, or whatever they're doing to work for the Tribal Council, or that it'll raise the wages out of hounds to some extent for the ones who are trying to hire people on the reservation rather than work in a mine on the reservation. Quite often they'll start down there. They learn to mine on the reservation. They might learn this trade there to start with, and as s.oon as they hear of some of the guys that come down that aremaking nearly double what they are, they come up and try to get a job. off the reservation. I'm sure that they would rather live on the reservation and work close to home, but not as long as there's that type of reduction in pay.KB.; Hlnm. That's very interesting. I haven't heard that mentioned before. Uh, what about the future for uranium mining in this area? How will it affect these Navajo miners? I understand that the jobs are getting harder and harder to get.
 SHUMWAYP AGE 1 8DS: Yeah, liut th.ey're heing filled almost entirely by the Navajos, at least in the area where we're working. I've got two men that are working as miners. I've got two or three more that are working in supervisory positions, but all the rest of them are Navajos. As far as I know, if I was to hire forty more people, all of them would be Navajos. I think that things will go on just about like they are.It's cut back as far as it can be cut back, as long as the two mills are going to stay in operation. And certainly, if any other mills come in, why, if B.CA was to--or Philip Minerals was to come back, why, it would almost double the number of men needed in the Ura Van MineralB.elt. And I would think that at least eighty percent of these would turn out to be Navajos that would be doing the work. There'd be--I don't think any of the contracts or any of the leases and so forth,would go to Navajos, hut nearly all of the leasers and contractorswould hire mostly Navajos.KR: Do you think there is a possibility of Philip Mineral coming back? DS: I never could understand why they haven't come back~ This is ideasthat I've put on tape for Clare Engle, but it looks to me like their having the market that they do for vanadium, arid the amount of vanadium ore, vanadium bearing ore, and the---?--- ore that theAEC is possibly going to release soon, why, I would think that BCAwould come back. They're the only logical ones to do this because they're the only ones b.esides Union Carbide in this area that has
 SHUMWAY P AGE 1 9any vanadium market. And they have got a lot of mines of their own.I think that they could acquire the ones that Climax has just shut down and come up with a good share of the ore that would be necessary to advertise a new plant. I think that they have got some equipment that they could use in this Shiprock mill down here. If they wereto try to move into the Ura Van Mineral Belt with this equipment, why, I would think that there's some money in it for them--from what I know- ahout it. But, I don't know, it's their business, and I would like to see them come hack because it would really help us as con- tractors and as leasors, and as miners, and so forth. We've got no competition with just Union Carbide and their two mills. I thinkthat the price of vanadium could come up some for the miner and possihly bring the price of uranium up to some extent. This is a long story, and most of it's already recorded anyway, but I would think that I would be considering it real strong.KB.: Now, as this effects the Navajo--1 was speaking to a gentleman in the Family Services Department here in Blanding, and he mentioned that there are training programs for the Indian in this area. Andhe mentioned that a training program was proposed to train Navajos for mining, b.ut that they- talked to one contractor and leasor, and he advised them against it, saying that there was going to be nomore future for the Navajo in mining. This was Clarence Black. And
 SHUMWAY PAGE 20so they dropped the idea of the training program. What do y-ou thinkof this?DS: Well, this is pure speculation to say that there's no more future inmining. This is like saying that there's no more future in farming, there's no more future in industry, that everything has gone to pot. This shows very little vision in the future, as near as I can tell. In my opinion, why, they're going to be needing miners as long as they're still making steel. And they're gonna be making steel as long as--as American industry is still forging ahead a little bit.I can't agree with.him or with anybody else that there's no futurein mining or farming or industry, manufacturing, and so forth. Uh,I don't know what he's basing it on. Probably, if he's basing it on the fact that most of the mines are mined out, why, this has been thehistory of mining all through the ages. But anytime American industry wants mining-....any mining product, all they've got to do is make the price right, and we'll have it running out of their ears again injust a little while. They figured at one time that nearly all ofthe uranit.UU was right here in Ura Van Mineral Belt, and there wasn't enough of it so they went to Africa and they went to Canada and diff- erent places and paid a higher price to get some of it. When they started paying the miners a decent price, why, it wasn't very long till we had ore in nearly--well, in lots of states and in abundance.
 SHUMWAY PAGE 21Right now, why, they're worried about their being able to make enough uranium for what these large generators will be needing fiy 1980.But all they've got to do is make the price right, and we'll damn sure soon have it for them. As with anything else, I don't care whether it's. gold or silver, or anything else, why, if we can't,we'll go somewhere else and find it for them, and produce it insuch an abundance that they won't need it all before long. And this is the way I feel ab.out the mining industry. We can do the same,of course, with agriculture. There's a lot of the farms that are being paid for not producing, and so forth. But American industry-- the land of America, the land of Mexico, or anyplace else, if the price is right, why, we can produce anything that they need. I don't care whether they figure they've got an overpopulation or sc0mething else. I think that the Lord knew what He was doing when He told people to multiply and replenish the earth, and there areplenty of natural resources to support any amount of people or any needs of the people. They don't even have to go to the oceans to feed people yet. Anytime that the price is right, why, we certainly have plenty of whatever they need that can be bought at that price. And it's only money that they're using to buy it with, anyway. SoI think that there's very little vision in somebody saying that there's no need for training people for this particular industry
 SHUMWAY- PAGE 22b.ecause it's going down th.e drain anyway.KB.: Would you hire people who have gone through training programs suchas this? Do you think it would he a good thing?DS: Uh, right now, why, there's plenty of them already trained becausethe industry was accelerated at one time. I think that these govern- ment training prograrns--they don't know how to train people. I'd rather take a green man, and have some miners that I've got starthim out on a training program so that he could effectively produce to start with. And I can train him myself or train him on the job, I think, b.etter than these government agencies can train him.KB~: Mayhe this was really what Clarence Black was getting at when he told them--DS: Well, this--this is--KB~ He didn't want to tell it to their face.DS': This is that elderly fellow, Clarence Black, that we're talking about,or is it one of the~-?---?KR: No, he's--he's not elderly. It's prob.ahly Juniors, the one with theairplane. In fact, he's flying a couple of our people around rightnow. Have you had any experience obtaining leases on the reservation? DS: Uh, some, yes.KB: But--DS: Not from the TribBl Council. There were leases that were already in
 SHUMWAY PAGE 23effect, or contracts that were already on lease to larger companies or s.omething this w..ay. B.ut it can be done. If I knew some ground that I wanted to get, I think that you have to get a Navajo partner, and then there's some dead weight to be carried there, and so forth. It isn't necessarily dead weight. He can probably carry his end of things, and if you had the right one, why, he'd be a real asset to you. But in most cases, why, you get somebody that knows where this ore body is, or knows where there's some ore, and you more or less carry him.just to ohtain the lease. He gets a percentage of thenet income,. or something this way, just for being there, or justbecause you've got to have him or something this way.KB.: Is th.is a deterrent for prospecting on the reservation, do you think? DS: I don't know that I'm hardly qualified to comment on that as to--as to whether this is good or whether it's bad. I'm sure that it's instigated to help the tribe and it's something that has evolved within the Tribal Council itself, and so forth. But I would think that the b.est setup would be for them to accept a royalty of some kind, preferably, one that would he equitable to both sides, both the leasor and Tribal Council, and anytime that one or another tries toget too hoggish, why, it isn't good for either one. And yet, as long as it's an equitable thing, why, both of them stands to a max- imum amount of money out of this. And if you could reach that
 SHUMWAY PAGE 24equitahle stage, where it was just right for both sides, why, I think that this w.:ould he the ideal situation rather than having some deadheat capitalizing on something that should go to the Trib.al Council and to all of the people. Unless, or course, this is some man that has gone out on his own and has discovered this ground. Certainly then, he has a right to whatever he can extract from s.ome White constractors, something this way.KB.: Have you paid royalties to the Tribal Council on your leases? DS: Not, not directly. It went to B.CA, and then--the only ones thatI've worked there have been through BCA.KB.: Do you know what kind of royalties they were paying?DS: No, hut I think that it was kind of on a.sliding scale of some kind.The hetter ore would probably hring a little more royalty, and the lower grade may very little royalty, but I don't know exactly how that went.KB.: Do you think, then, that if it was on a sliding scale, that they were always honest with the Tribal Council on the assays?DS: Well, no, I know that they weren't. I've got firsthand information to have the knowledge that they weren't always honest. Now theymay have been ninety percent of the time, but to some extent, why, they weren't always honest. I wouldn't say what company wasn't orwhat company was, and whether any of them were entirely honest or not.
 SHUMWAY PAGE 25This involves a lot of other things. They're not entirely honestat the mills when it comes time to settle with the White ore sellers, and the mine operators, because to some extent, they can't be. They've got factors within their plant whereby sometimes an ore isn't mean- ingful to their plant, where they can't get more than fifty percent recovery on it. Well, they can't very well give you an honest assay, and pay you everything that there is in it when they can only recover half of it. I can see their point on this, and to some extent thismay have b.een so on the ores on the reservation. But no, they manageto beat the Tribal Council out of a good share of their royalty on one large ore body that I know of. Yet they've done the same thingto s.ome White people at times. We as contractors or leasors even knew that we were only getting about half of what was in our ore,but we agreed that this was still better than being shut down because we were making a profit off of it. And this is what we're looking for. We don't want to shut down something that we are making a good profit off of. So we put up with this to some extent, ourselves, and any leasor that thinks that they always get a hundred percent of-- get paid for hundred percent of the values that's in their ore, why, they're only kidding themselves because these companies can't afford to pay that all the time. They have got certain factors that theyhave to live with. Their mills don't make a hundred percent recovery,
 SHUMWAY PAGE 26KB·DS:and therefore, they can't very well always pay a hundred percent. Have you had any dealings with the Navajo ·mill there in Shiprock? I've shipped lots of ore there. yes. In fact, we were even renting their trucks for a long time that ore went down there, both purchase ore, and contract ore. In fact, there was quite a period of time there that we would have been shipping at least--oh, it had been,two, three, or four hundred tons a day that we shipped down there s.ometimes. I think that was for a year or two there we were shipping twenty to forty percent--twenty to fifty percent of the ore that was running that mill.Was this ore that you had obtained from your leases on the reservation or was some of it off the reservation?Mos.t of it came from off the reservation. We run the Delaney Prop- erties th.ere when we was making a hundred ton of ore a day there,and we was making quite a little ore in LaSalle Creek, and quite a little over in Dry Valley and East Canyon, and different places that, at that time, nearly all of it was going tc Shiprock. Just prior to their shutting down the Shiprock plant, or for the last two or threeyears that it was in operation, why, a good share of our ore went toKB.:DS:Shiprock, and w.e were producing lots of ore at that time.KB:.: What do you helieve is the primary reason for closing down the Navajom ill in Shiprock?DS.: Well, I don't know. This goes into a phase that there was quite a
 SHUMWAY PAGE 27long haul. I think that they--the mines were at about their lowest ebb, the BCA mines. They didn't have enough ore reserve to continueto feed that plant. Uh, they had done a lot of drilling on the reserv- ation and their mines were down. They, at that time, they shouldhave tried to get some of these AEC leases turned loose. They weren't making a profit from this end at least, and I think that about that time they got some ore coming from Africa. Well, it's a by-productof the st'.eel mines over there--concentrate of vanadium that theycould just ship over here, mill, and make more of a profit off itthan they could b.y mining their own mines in the Ura Van MineralBelt. But I'm sure that it was the factor of the long hauJ.. They had to haul it from the Ura Van Mineral Belt, most of the ore, to Shiprock, and then the mines didn't have a good reserve. They didn't have res.erves enough that they could see where they could continue tofeed that mill. There was still Climax in there at that time. It's always b.een my opinion that that went the wrong direction, thatPhilip Minerals leased their claims to Climax. But they had another factor going for them there, too. They could buy the ore hack. In fact, Climax didn't have any vanadium market, so they would get thevanadium back from Climax, and then it would be shipped to Ohio--in their Ohio plants. They'd make the bigger money off it. This was always. a profitab.le thing, turning this Black Cake, or the vanadium--
 SHUMWAY PAGE 28the fused vanadium to ferral vanadium. The ferral vanadium is nearing,oh, five dollars a pound right now. KR: Oh, it is?DS: And the ore could probably be purchased at that time from Climax for mayhe a dollar and a quarter, or something like that, a pound. Ands.o the big end of it, and the profitable end was taking the--was takingthe fused vanadium and turning it to ferral vanadium, and they stillhave this going for them. So this is probably why they leased their mines to Climax, and then hought the ore back from Climax. But nowthey don't have this advantage, and I still think that they could getthe Climax mines and get their share of these AEC--these mineralleases that will be coming back in if they ever come up with some competition. I would hope that AEC doesn't turn loose these blocksjust to Union Carbide b.ecause this would put every one of us contractors, or at least the leasors selling purchase ore, why, we would be out ofb.usiness, I feel, hecause of these big government blocks of ore that are capahle of feeding these mills in their entirety. They wouldn't need any ore from anywhere else, and certainly they're not going to pay me three or four dollars a pound for uranium and forty-two cents a pound for vanadium at the Black, and the Blue Cap, and so forth,if they can go over here and mine ore that they're probably getting for twenty-five cents a pound for the uranium, and nothing on the
 SHUMWAY PAGE 29vanadium on the lease--or the mineral lease which is cash royalty.If they're paying a cash royalty for this, why, the AEC thinks that they've got six million pounds, and actually they've got sixty million pounds. They don't know it, I don't think, but Union Carbide does.So actually, if they pay this on a cash royalty, why, they'd paymaybe fifty cents a pound for the u o that's in it, which would 38give them what--about three million dollars. Well, they may haveto pay a dollar a pound for it on cash royalty, and that would give them s.ix million pounds for six million dollars. But when it turns out to be sixty million pounds instead of a dollar a pound, they're paying ten cents. a pound. And so, I can't see where it would do us any good to have these mineral leases turned loose. It'd ruin the small miner. B.ut it'd certainly put Union Carbide on the gravy train for about ten years, or something this way, and enough to feed both of them plants with some real cheap ore that they get from we, the people, or from Uncle Sam. My idea of this would be to get anothermill back in and then put it on a royalty basis--a royalty bid basis. We contractors would then bid--I would like to have two or three or four or five of these mineral leases on a fifty-fifty basis. I'd pay fifty percent royalty. And that way, why, instead of paying six million dollars on a cash royalty basis, which is a dollar a pound, w.hy·, I'd be paying about a dollar and a half a pound on the uranium
 SHUMWAY PAGE 30that's in it for the sixty million pounds, which would amount to ninety million dollars rather then six million dollars. The people of the United Stated would make prpbably at least sixty million dollars off of these if it goes that route. But the other route, with no competition to Union Carbide, I couldn't afford to bid a thing if I had ten million dollars, and would buy two of these leases from Uncle Sam and figure on keeping what was left over to operate them with. I could b.e told by Union Carbide, "Well fine, you'vegot a great hig bunch of good ore, you just go down there and lookat it, or build a mill if you want to," or something like this.And they've got you. You just don't have a chance, neither does anyhody else. One of these big oil companies, if they was to comein and get all of this property, why, they still don't have anyvanadium market. They can't compete with Union Carbide on a royalty bid basis against something like Union Carbide which has all the vanadium market tied up. But BCA has all of these advantages that Union Carbide has got, so you'd think that they would be the ones that would come back in. And yet, they don't show any desire to come hack, or any indications that they are about to come back. But I'd sure like to see them come back.KB~ I bet you would. Well, I just have one last question. Do you think-- do you feel the mines out on the reservation are about played out,
 SHUMWAY PAGE 31or do you think there is any future out there yet?DS: This goes back to that same--KB.: The.;same~-- ·DS: --story that I told you before. If the price is right, why, there'sa niillio.n of tons of good ore yet on the reservation that private industry will find, but, there again, you might have to change the leases. a little. They might have to change their policy on leasing and s·o forth. The reason that Mexico isn't as progressive a country as the United States is because they don't have the right laws down there. Their government is such that if private industry goes inand s:pends a bunch of money, they might lose it. Well, nobody is going to go this route. But there's still a lot of ore on the reserv- ation. If the price was right, and private industry was given free- - - - - - - "r'-e"--i"=n--=---t=-o=---go there on a ro alty basis that 'they could live with, and one that would he equitable to the Tribal ·council and equitable to the mining industry, why, there's lots of ore there yet.KB:.: Do you think the Tribal Council realizes this?DS: Uh--KB': I mean certainly they're going to want more revenue. They claim thattheir revenue has been out played out now. DS.: Well, they've got oil royalties coming in. KB.; Yeah, they have the oil coming in, hut--
 SHUMWAY P AGE 3 2DS: Uh, their revenue from mining is about done, I can see that. But, maybe there's so much of it down around Grant's or Ambrosia Lake area, or there's so much of it up in Wyoming and different places thatthere's no need of getting some off of the reservation. They can produce it cheaper up here in known ore bodies. Certainly they'vegot an awful lot of it found, and all they've got to do to find a bunch more is to up the price maybe fifty cents or something like that. That will make--that will almost daub.le the reserves. Thetrue definition of ore is the mineral that can be profitably extract- ed, and. up there they've got a lot of it that--there's an awful lotof uranium around, but it is so marginal that you're just trading dollars so it isn't considered ore. It isn't considered ore reserves.And yet, if the price went up by one dollar, why it would probablyjus:t ah.ou-t·-douhie the -knowu-·re-serves ·th·ere;- - And- if i-t- went--up bytwo dollars a pound from, say, six dollars up to eight dollars, why, private industry would go there and find twice as much as what they've already got. And this is all that they need on the reservation isfor the price to be right and they'll find way more than has been mined. I don't think that they've mined ten percent of it off theres·ervation. It might b.e the easy part of it, but ninety percent of it is still there waiting to be found when the price is right. But it isn't going to be found if there's no market for it.KR: Well, thank you very much, and--