 CATO SELLSFort Defiance, Arizona Tape No. 3An interview by Kathy Biel July 31, 1970American West Center University of Utah Uranium History Series
 Table of ContentsBackground • • • 1 Mining Business 3 Uranium on the Reservation. 5 Navajo Workers••• 9 Climax Corporation. 18 Prospects for More Mining. 23
 THIS IS AN INTERVIEW WITH MR. CATO SELLS, A NAVAJO PROSPECTOR, MINE OWNER, CONTRACTOR, AND PRESENTLY THE SUPERINTENDENT OF WATER DEVELOPMENT FOR THE NAVAJO TRIBE. THIS IS AN INTERVIEW FOR THE UNIVERSITY OF UTAH AND CALIFORNIA STATE COLLEGE AT FULLERTON,THE URANIUM INDUSTRY ORAL HISTORY PROJECT. THE INTERVIEW TOOK PLACE IN MR. SELLS~ OFFICE OF THE TRIBAL WATER DEVELOPMENT AT FORT DEFIANCE, AT 3:30 IN THE AFTERNOON ON JULY 31ST, 1970. THEINTERVIEWER IS KATHY BIEL.KB: Mr. Sells, I'd like to begin our interview by having you give me a little bit ab.out your background, where you were born, where you lived, where you had your education--just anything about your family background.CS: Uh, I was born on the Navajo reservation over west of Shiprock,in San Juan County, New Mexico. Actually, there's nothing there-- just a wide place in the road. And I went to school in Shiprock originally. That's where I started. And from Shiprock, I wentto California. I went to school in Riverside.KB: Sherman Institute?CS: Uh, I went to Sherman Institute, and I got--got through then, andI went on into town, and to Riverside, and I went and finished High School there at Polytech High School in 1927. And this is the extent of my formal education. And we have five children, and they all have a college degree. They're all over the countrynow.KB.: Your children?
 SELLS PAGE 2CS:KB.:CS:KB:CS: KB,: CS:Y es.Uh huh. What was your first job as a young man when you got outof high school?Well, my first major job that I took was--in my high school, Itook the pre-vocational high school course. I took up automobile. And so I'd start out as an automobile mechanic, and I spend about sixteen, eighteen year in that garage.Was this in Riverside?No, I came back here on the reservation.Oh, you came back here?Yes, and I spent about that many years, and then back in 1943,I started off by myself--in business for myself. Uh, it wasuntil I went to work for the tribe that I was on my own. I had the--this garage, then I had two garages, and I was in the trucking business in Four Corners area during the uranium period. I was also in construction. Half of the Navajo reservation constructing dams, and reservoirs, and things. And also I was in the mining operation--mining and leasing, and working on some of the leases that I had on the reservation. And I liquidated everything Ihad back in 1958, and I temporarily went into retirement untilI took this job here back in 1961, and here I am. KB.: And what is your job here?
 SELLSPAGE 3CS:KB.:CS:I'm the Superintendant of Water Development of the Navajo Tribe in an area of 25,000 square miles.My goodness. So you were talked out of your retirement to come back to quite a responsible job here.Well, I figured that the reservation had been good to me, andI felt uh, more obligated to help these people. And I figured perhaps I'd come back for five years, but I've been here since'61. Here it is '70. So I don't know. The more you do, there's more to be done. So actually, I don't know what the future holds for me. I'd like to get back on, and--What would you do, if you could talk yourself into leaving?Well, I--I thinkg I'd quit and go traveling. Travel the world. Oh, you would?Yes.Oh--Well, let's get back to your mining days. That's what I'm interested in. You say you were leasing and even prospecting at the same time you had your trucking business? Working construction?KB:CS:KB,: CS: KB,:CS: Originally, I--uh, was in--I had one garage, and I started to prospect on the reservation soon after the Second World War.We worked out a program with the Navajo tribe, where the Navajo individual could go out and prospect and take leases and work
 SELLS PAGE 4some of--a lot of the Navajo boys had worked a lot of mines.Some of them had gone in with the other people--other companies. KB: B.C.A's?CS: The B.C.A's Climax Uranium Company and the other people--someof the smaller people. So, I was instrumental in bringing in enough company--Climax Uranium Company out in Grand Junction to--KB: You brought them out?CS: Yeah, I brought them into the reservation for--for the developmentof this project for this uranium.KB:: How did you do this?CS: Well, I contacted those people, and I went up and talked to themand talked them into coming on the reservation and helping me prospect, help me mine, help me develop to see--so I finally got them talked into it. They came in, and we developed quite a program. We were--we were one of the big operators, and for a long time we were--we stayed on this operation about as long as anybody, that is, during the time that the Atomic Energy Connnission wason the reservation. And this was the only market we had, wasthe government. So consequently, the government can turn anything up over a period of one day. This is what happened. They closedall Projects, and they only set a certain date for any allocation made up to the prior--1 mean prior to this lease or to this date,
 SELLSPAGE 5or any development that was done prior to this date was all allocated to the production of ore to a certain period, 1970.So consequently, there was no market, and the market began togo down, and the only source of market we had was the AtomicEnergy Connnission. Now, this is turning--uh, the market willbe a market for everybody. I think that now that this new industry will come in on a new basis, it's a new phase altogether. And everybody would be on their own, and I'm very much interested to get back in again, to--in, even the government was new at this type of thing. I think that we learned lots of things that we could apply today ifwe went back in there. I think that the old body that we thought we had, I don't think that we touched it. I think that the old body was left out there untouched, so I think we've got--we havea big, big potential left on our reservation. The only--the mine that were mined was the exposed ore. And there were no, actually,no drilling development conducted on the reservation.KB.: What do you think will be needed to bring this new interestabout?CS: We need to interest the--the Navajo tribe, the Navajo people.You think there is a future for uranium on reservation lands yet?KB.:CS: Definitely. There is a big, big opportunity because when we went
 SELLSPAGE 6KB:CS:KB.: CS:The government has held this thing up as of now. The tribal government, or--?No.Or the federal government1The BIA has held this thing now back in Washington. I think that they should give it back to the Navajo tribe and let the Navajo tribe run this--not only the oil, but the uranium; all the resource development on the Navajo reservation, instead of BIA hanging on to these things here. I think that we could probably do a hetter job and do it a lot faster, something that is competitive with the outside world. I think that we need to getout, and we need to compete with the outside world because we have to meet those prices and we need to bring the industry in here that has the know-how, has the capability of financing all ofthis exploration because it is an expensive operation.You don't see that it's .possible for the Tribal Council to financeKB.:this industry themselves then?CS: Well, I think that--that this is very possible. But as of now,I think that we would have to have more know-how, that we need-- I think we need a bigger company to come in to explore for this type of thing. I think that there are ways--there are ways that if we brought in the big companys, we could help ourselves, by
 SELLSPAGE 7KR: CS:checker-boarding the leases instead of giving the--just giving them a whole chunk of land and letting them develop and get all this. I think that by checker-boarding, what I mean is this section up here we'd least to them, and we'd leave here reserved for us the two sections. We'd leave this to the company-- That's like the railroads did.Yes. And let them block this thing out. And when they got ore here and ore here, we know we got ore in between here, in our area. This would bring more money, higher prices for what wewant to do. Then we can afford to go in and mine these ourselves, or drill these ourselves on the leases because it's know to be more economical, a more business-like manner. This is the way the big companies operate anyway.Wouldn't you have to wait until the price of uranium goes back up? It's not too--the price of uranium is down right now, but is coming back up. I understand that the price will be back effectiveab.out '73. The finished product is about six dollars a pound.I understand it'll be around a little or seven dollars in '73 or '74. So, I think that we ought to be ready to get something done. so that something gets started, so that we can be readyKB: CS:when the market is here.KB.: Can the Tribal Council begin promoting to interest industries,
 SELLSPAGE 8CS:much like you did with Climax, contact them, or say--Well, I think--I think that the--not so much the Council, butthe individual people, the individual Navajos because thereare a lot of Navajos ·o.ut there who wt:er.e .im bli;ts :iJ.rldus.t'ry, w.ho were in this business. Individual Navajos, I think, know more about the deposits, or where the deposits can be because they worked with these things and are familiar with the formations and you know what formations can be found. I think that if they left a lot and created some incentive, I think that would build us right back up again. We've got three mills that are down and we need to get back up and put them back into operation.Such as the Navajo mill in Shiprock, and--?One at Mexican Hat, and one east of Tuba City.And also this would provide jobs for those miners who had to go off the reservation to find more mining jobs. Wouldn't thisKB.:CS:KB:.b.ring them back?CS: Yes, a lot of these Navajos are really capable with their hands.And they were very good operators, and now that they have to go off the reservation to work, I think this will create a lot more problems for these people at home. So they can be home. AndI can't for the life of me see that there is not--we haven't mined all the ore. I think--I don't think we've touched the surface
 SELLSPAGE 9KB:of the development.I know when I've spoken to them up in Salt Creek, or Utah, that they would much prefer to be on the reservation mining, but there just aren't any jobs left. Of course, all the mines are shut down. Uh, I'd like to go back to your involvement with Climax. What kind of a working agreement did you have with them? Wereyou in partnership with them, or just--you contacted them andtold them about these deposits. What did they do for you, then? The Navajo tribe had the regulation at that time that we couldgo our and b.ring whoever we want to onto the reservation, and there was a certain royalty ore right that we got by gettingthese people into production. And some of them we--worked someof the mines myself, and some of thefl, Climax worked some of these properties.So you were an independent miner and also leasing with Climax?Yes, uh huh.When you were an independent miner, were you hiring any men, or were you doing it all yourself?No, I had--I was hiring--I had done all my hiring and the operation does that independently.Uh huh. Were these all Navajo miners?CS:KB.: CS: KB.:CS:KB.:CS: Well, all Navajo miners, but I had a foreman who usually--someone
  SELLSPAGE 10KB:CS:KB:CS:KB.:CS:KB.: CS: K B .. : CS: KB.,:that had a lot of background, a lot of experience in mining. The foreman was Navajo also?No.He was--He was a White man. But eventually, I trained Navajos in theend and ended up with Navajo foreman.Uh huh. Did you have any labor problems, or any working relation problems with any of your employees?No, we never had any problem. We never had any labor problemswith any of the White employees.They didn't mind the White foremen?Oh no, they got along fine.They did?Oh yes. We got along fine.Did you do any of the actual work in the mine yourself, such asworking the buggies or the jackhannner or any of these thingsduring that time?CS: I didn t have the time.KB: You didn't have the time?CS: I was in five business at the time.KB.: Well, I should say you would not. Five businesses. Well, I got the trucking, and the construction, and the mining--
 SELLSPAGE 11CS:KB:CS: KB: CS: KB: CS: KB: CS:KB: CS: KB.: CS:KB:Two--two garages.And the garages. You were a busy man weren't you?Yes, I was.No wonder you wanted to retire.Y es.Have you held on to these leases, or have you let them go back?W ell, they--they expired.They expired? Could you go out again and stake them again?Sure, just as soon as they change their regulations, I'm alreadyto go.You're are ready to go? But you're going to go traveling.I'll do that too.Oh, you'11 do that too.Well, you see, I don't work in the mine. I get these people to work, I've got people out there I can depend on, I can do anything I want to. That's what I did before.That's marvelous. What kind of pay were you giving your employees?Were you paying by hour, or were you giving them contract work? CS: By the hour.KR: B:y the hour?CS: Y es.KB-: Any reason why you weren't using contract?
 SELLS PAGE 12CS: A reason why I didn't contract? Yes. The Navajos wouldn't work for contract because they weren.'t sure of their capacity, what they could do. They'd rather work on an hourly basis.KB: I see. Did any of the regulations, the mining regulations, inter- fere with your mining? Such as the inspectors coming out and inspecting the ventilation and inspecting for radon. Did you have any problems in this area1CS: No, no, we didn't. We didn't have any problems as far as regulation goes. They didn't--they didn't hinder us or anything.KB,: Uh, have you seen any accident in your mines?CS: Uh, we didn't have any accidents that I know of, in our mines. KB..: You didn't?CS: No.KB: What would he the main danger working in a mine?CS: Well, the main danger of working in a mine is when you get readyto blast. Make sure that everything is put in a safe place. Then these working, make sμre that you ceilings are safe, and you test these everyday and make sure that---?------?--- loose rock from the bottom to the top, so that they can be---?---. Because constantly you're shooting those mines, and if you don'thave everything secure, you're liable to have something falling off, or caving in. We didn't have any problem. We had precaution
 SELLS PAGE 13against what may cause you to have an accident. You have toanticipate all of these.KB-: I see. Do you find it very easy to train your miners? Did theywant to go from one job to another and progress from nothing toall of them had experience at one time or another working for-- in there. Uh, I didn't find any problem with these people notwanting ·to work. They were all raring to--raring to work, I watched the~ and was all the time looking for somebody to take care of my operation because I had a lot of operation leaders in these people. And I made foremen out of the people thatI thought would make me good foremen, and all of this--and inmy trucking office. I had three trucks, and also I had a trucking office. I had three trucks, and also I had a trucking foremanin that group. So I had a supervisor in each one of these oper- ations.KB.: So you were able to find leaders--leadership ·ability among your workers?CS: Yes, they have--they have the leadership ability, yes, because they're interested in work. They like to stay on the reservation and work. And s9IIle of these boys that I had, didn't have any---?---Did they want to--in other words, were they ambitious? CS: These Navajos that I had were very good workers. Uh, practically
 SELLS PAGE 14education, but that didn't prevent them from being the best ofanything.KB: Uh huh. Now I have spoken to other mining operators off thereservation, and they--some of them have complained abouttheir Navajo employees because mainly because of their undepend- ab~lity. They speak of Navajo time, They can never depend on themen coming back to work the next Monday after their--right after their three or four days off. Did you experience this here on the reservation?CS: I know that some of those big operators, bigger companies were having turnovers. But my people, the people that I worked with lived right in the vicinity of my mining operation. I didn't have this problem. In fact, I always told those people that I want them here a certain day, or a certain number of days for working. They didn't--if they didn't come, they could look someplace else because I want dependable peopJe. And I had dependab.le people, and I didn't have no problem.KB.: Do you think the difference might be that.they were working here on the reservation and not away from their own people? Do you think that would be the difference?CS: I think the--some of the differences here in my own department now is that the--away from the reservation, they have an access
 SELLSPAGE 15KB: CS:to a lot of things out there, and maybe they--when they get home, they're close to a bar, close to liquor joints. and this may have something to do with interference. But here we don't have that. We didn't have it after--And maybe they're homesick too.They're away from home, and they weren't exactly satisfied with the country, and they may be homesick, like you said, I don't know. We didn't--actually I didn't have any problems with my people.KB: Was your work week a regular work week, or did you just work them ten days, give them four days off, or allow them three?CS: We worked a five-day week.KB.: You worked a regular work week? Now, you've been in this areafor a long time and have been a business man, have been active in trihal government. How do you view the development, or the effects of the mining industry here on the reservation? How has it affected the people, or the government, or just what are yourviews in this area?CS: Well, I think that the mining is just like anything else. It'sone facet of the economy on a reservation, and is like anything else. I think if we had normal mining to support three mills, itwould be a tremendous impact on the economy of the people while
 SELLS PAGE 16they're living here on the reservation. I think that as long as it is here, some effort·should be pursued to develop the resources that we have on our reservation.KB: Well, or course now it's at a low ebb what of these miners who-- who perhaps b.egan working in the mines, and this was their first wage-earning job. They were making much more money than they were accustomed to mayb.e with their sheep or goats. And then mines played out, or they closed the mines down, and the men weren't trained for any other jobs other than mining. How did this affect them?CS: Well, I don't think it would affect these people as it would any place else because·! think that because these people--their income to b.egin with was lower. And they always had a few head of sheep that they could fall back on. They existed· a lot better than a family that moved to a town. They'd make a high wage during a construction period perhaps, then he's out of a job for two or three months looking for one. I think it would have a lotmore economic impact on him. He'd be lost there looking for a job. then, these Navajos, because they can go--can go right b.ack to like they were before. Anything that is done to supplement their income, I think should be done here on the reservation, ifat all possible. Especially since we have the resources here to
 SELLSPAGE 17KB:CS:develop.You don't think then, that it bothered them, having once made quite a hit of money, then having to go back to their old way of living their old economic level. It didn't bother them? Well, I think--T think it bothers everybody. I don't think--I think it bothers people. You make a lot of money, then you don't make very much money. I think that it has to effect all human beings, to an extent. B,ut this may have helped some of these people to go out and search for a job; this may be one reason why some of these people are working up in Colorado, in Utah, up there working in these mines ·because they made money at one time. This was what they--what they were following.They became accustomed to it?Yes, uh huh.Uh, were these people ready for the sudden influx of economy? In other words, the concensus of opinion it seems to be, at least off the reservation is that these Navajos miner-s,:·iWill ·:-.take ;:thei:r paycheck and just spend it on anything, and not save for the future at all. They're not used to handling that much money. Do you see this as a problem?KB.: CS: KB..:CS: Uh, well it is, I think, to the extent that these people have not learned to bank their money, have not learned to put it into
 SELLS PAGE 18savings, and things. I think that this will come generally astime--as we grow into--it may probably take another generation. KB: I see, uh huh. Are you--is Climax still operating off thereservation? Doesn't it have mines up in Colorado somewhere? CS: Uh, Climax is--it's a small company out of another big mergerthat they've heen having. They had had this uranium mill at Grand Junction and they were figuring on closing it down because the decline of the market and the uranium situation at the time. I think that a lot of the companies probably feel the same way unless those companies had contracts and extend it into a period heyond '70.KB.: Uh huh.CS: And Climax was figuring oh--I don't know the last time I talkedto some of these people, they---?--- or the manager didn't knowexactly what they wanted to do.KB: Would you want to bring Climax back in here once it opened upagain? Is that who you would like to contact and bring in todevelop?CS: Not necessarily.KB: Not necessarily?CS: No, not necessarily. I think any large company would have thetechnology of this b.usines-s. I think that they can get the know-
 SELLSPAGE 19KB.:CS: KB:CS: KB.: CS: KB.: CS:KB: CS:KB.:how, not necessarily from Climax--I think from any company.I don't care who they may be.And would you say that--do you helieve that the Navajo mill at Ship- rock, for instance, would open up again?Uh, it's just sitting there waiting for someone to buy it.Yes, I know. There's just the plant manager there now sitting at a desk doing nothing. He was rather embarrassed when I walkedin on him.Yes, did you do an interview with him?I wanted to.What's his name?Mr. Daniel.Oh yeah. He was the plant st.iperintendant, wasn't he, or managerthere b.efore?Yeah.Yeah, he could probably tell you a lot about me that I couldn't tell you.·Oh, he didn't seem to want to talk. He said he'd think about it, and let me know. He didn't have the time then, but he was rather guarded. He was afraid I would probe a little too deeply, I think, into his relations with the BCA, and the--CS: This is probably what it is. He would probably have to get
 SELLS PAGE 20sanction from the B.CA and from Mineral City. ---?--- Mineralsand BCA merged just before they close this one up.KB: Yes, I know. And I tried to assure him that this wasn't myarea of interest. I was interested only in the mill as an employer of the Navajo people on the reservation, but even then he said he'd have to consider it. Now I'm still waiting to hear from him.CS: Well, he'd probably have to get it from his headquarters. KB: I'm sure this is what it is.CS: Well, you know Mr. Page Edward?KB.: Page Edward? No.CS: Well, he's the big wheel for that, and he used to live in Durango. KB: He lived in Grant?CS: In Durango.KB:.: Durango? And what was his position?CS: He's--I think he's the general manager of the BCA Western Division in western United States.KB.: He's probably been contacted b.y one of our other research team members. We broke up into areas of specialty because we had to do quite a bit of research before we camee Such as, I'm inter- viewing all Navajo people who have been· involved in the industry.CS: Oh, yes. The general concensus of the Navajo, they want that?
 SELLSPAGE 21KB.:CS: KB:CS: KB: CS:KB_: CS: KB-.: CS: KB.: CS:Yes, they do. Even Mr. Tabohazto thought he'd like to try it.At age seventy-three, he was willing to go again.He's seventy-three? Yeah, he was in it quite a bit.Uh, well, now he was involved with the professor who's ~ directing this project, Dr. Gary Shumway, whose family was involved inthe uranium industry quite a bit. _His father, Aris Shumway even came down on the reservation after a few claims, I guess. Shumway--that sounds like a Mormon up in Utah.Yes, it is.~eah, I was involved with some of the Shumways up in Monument V alley.In Monument V alley? You worked up in Monument V alley also? Yes, I had a claim. I had claims up there in Monument Valley. Oh, you did?Yes.What were the names of your claims?--?--- Uh, I was right next to BCA.KB.: Momnnent Numb.er One and Number Two?CS: Yes. See this is--this Monument one. And monument Number Two,I was right next to Monument Number Two. KB.: Oh, you were?CS: This was the biggest mine in the United States at any time.
 SELLS PAGE 22KB: Yes, I know.CS: And, there's---?--- You ever been over there?KB.: Yes, I've b.een through it. I have to go back again and contactsome people I have out there.CS: I had bigger acres than he did.KB: You did?CS: Yes. Mine--the B.CA, I made a sandwich out of them. I used theirsame common ties to this here.KB·.: You were on both sides of them then?CS: This is the B.CA. Yes, this is east, and this is west, north,and south and there's a wash---?--- I was on both sides of the B£A in Monument Valley. And then they had another claim. They had--across the wash, there wash a little knoll that stuck out like that. They only had, I think, about two and one-half acres, andI stuck 160 acres over the top---?------?---KB.: You say you thought these claims were called Cato I and Cato II? CS: Y es.KB.: That sandwiched B.CA here?CS: Yes. This side was Cato I, and I think this was Cato II.KB.: Uh huh. And were these good claims for you?CS: Yes, uh huh, these were definitely good claims.KB.: Did you have these in conjunction with Climax, or were you mining
 CS:KB:CS:KB:CS:these independently?It was in conjunction with Climax Mining Company. Then after they got through, they leased them back to me, and I went and worked these over some more.Clearn them out?Yes, you never get--you never get through. Lots of times they'll go off and leave a lot of ore. This was--they thought they were through. Couldntt find no -more ore after this.Do you think there is still more ore in this area? Is this the area you were thinking of when you said there was a lot?Well, I don't know, there could be. I think perhaps deep drilling may reveal something, but this don't--this might be the only one. There could be other places in the vicinity that by drilling, you might be able to find some. But no, I didn't have--I didn't have any reference to this particular claim.thousand, thousands of acres that I haven't mined, that wehaven't actually mined. I know that possibly there is ore because-- since that time, the other companies were drilling into a deeper formation. They found a lot of ore that is--there's a lot morein the place where we found it.SELLS PAGE 23Uh huh. Just in general?KB.:CS: But there are other areas that I have, some bigger areas--ten
 SELLS PAGE 24KB: But, this would run your mining costs way up i f you had to dri l l down deeper wouldn't it?CS: Yeah, but then if it's feasible, if there's enough deposit down there, your mining costs you can always get back easy.KB.: Uh huh. What would you take, fresh samples out of different areas?CS:No, you drill into a certain formation that you want to drill to,and dig samples, and see what you find. This is what they find lately--on the basis of my experience in drilling for uranium inthe same formation in so far as it comes from here. They went deeper into the other formation, which would then tell if it had any ore.I see.The same--the same is true with ADS at the time when the found ore. They stopped to---?--- explore, and then they stopped to explore to see if there was anything in underneath. They didn't go toany particular formation.How long did you have these claims out in Monument Valley?Ab.out ten years.About ten years? Did you shut your down just about the same time B-CA shut theirs down?This is practically all depleted now 'cause this was a high grade ore. This one little spot was a high grade ore, but what had happened to it, the BCA depleted this, they---?--- this out.KB: CS:KB.: CS: KB.:CS:
 SELLSPAGE 25And we got all of ours out. We hadn't any more high grade. Then what happened, after the BCA set up a mill, we took all the low grade uraniums through there. You see that's pretty well depleted. Unless we can drill and go deeper and find ore, that's---?--- to mine---?---.KB: I see. Well, I want to thank you for taking time out in your office here to talk to me, Mr. Sells, and I'll stop the recording now.