  GILMOR C. RITTER Grand Junction, Colorado Tape No. 77An interview by Richard Gibbs and Greg Brolin July 21, 1970American West Center University of Utah Uranium History Series
 Table of ContentsEarly Years on the Colorado Plateau . . . 1 Qualifications for Obtaining an A.E.C. Lease. 18 Disadvantages of an A.E.C. Lease. 24 Uranium Ore Purchasing Policy. 27 His Position..... . 30
 This is an interview for the Uuanium Industry Oral History Project for the. University of Utah-Cali.fornia State College at Fullerton. Gregg Brolin and Richard Gibos are interviewing Gilmer C. Ritter at the Atonri.c Energy Connnission Compound, Grand Junction, Colorado, on July 11, 1970.G: Mr. Ritter, first of all, I'd like to talk to you about the early years: of the A.E..C. here on the Colorado Plateau. I was wondering, are you familiar with the Union Mines Survey?R: Generally- I'm famili.ar with the Union :ttdnes Survey because during the first part of my work. with the Connnission, I worked on the i.ni..ti.al production bonus· and we were required to do research on specific areas and speci.fic properties and we found that we could us:e the Uni.on Mines: Survey area to provide data, was probably the only printed data of the time on these specific localities and on the specific property, I know quite a few people that were in- volved there.G: Could you name a few of those people?R: There was Hank Wordwall, there was John Emerson, Jack Robison, there was Tony Mastrovich, those are a few of the names that come to mind. There were many others that worked there at onetime or another that I may have met but I don't know.G: How accurate do you find the Union Mine Survey to be?R: Qui.te accurate. I don't know exactly what we're talking about. They located property- on the ground for us. Now this is one ofthe things that I was looking for. They did this quite accurately.They surveyed property. Now, they also did geology, they did s.ections, they sketched a great deal of surface geology and they
 R: identified the structures, identified the formation, and they did a lot of good mapping. They did have a considerable disad- vantage i.n that they didn't have drill work, drill holes, drill- ing to back them up and to give them good information for their secti_ems.G: Do you thi.nk that's why they underestimated the uranium reserves on the plateau?R: Oh yes,. I. do. Yeah. Because you can't go through and just flat surface geology. In the ye.ars in which they were doing this, they didn't know too much aoout the occurrences, you know. So they knew that carnotite and ros:coelite type ore occurred in the Morri.son formation. They still didn't have any idea as to the controls, but they, I'm sure had a lot of theories. But there was a great deal of information that we now have that they lacked.G:· This. survey--how large a part do you feel the survey played in the e.arly- A.E.C. procurement program?Quite a part, and perhaps it was significant. Perhaps I tend to underestimate the worth of the survey because it occurred before my- time. I think the--my personal belief is that the thing that's helped get the domestic industry off the ground was perhaps the fact that now the nitty gritty was at hand and we had to have the urani.um. Some people were instrumental in pushing the industry forward, recognized, grasped this fact, recognized it, and tookR:1some steps·, and the second, the guaranteed price that we had. Thepage 2
 R: commission guaranteed the price of uranium through March 31 of sixty-two. Now when they started this is in 1948, and then they by stages raised these guarantees; this to my way of thinking was the bas.is that really gave it tbe last push.G! What do you know about the early exploration by the A.E.C. on the Colorado Plateau?R: Well, the early explorati.on was ·conducted by the A.E.C. with the U.S. Geological Survey under contract running quite a number of drilling projects. The A.E.C. itself set up an exploration division with headquarters- firs:t in New York and then moved to here. The A.E.C, exploration division also sponsored and contracted for drilling pl!rograms. Now, fi.rst of all, they were looking for uranium, plain and simple. They wanted to find uranium that they could produce because we were starting to get cracking with the gaseous diffusion plants- and these things cost billions of dollars, andthey aren't worth a darn unless you got the uranium feed materials to put into them. So the government--the Commission withdrew a lot of land from the country under the Public Land Laws, and went i.n and this: land was withdrawn in areas which were expected toyi_eld uranium. Then they drilled it out. In the early days from '·49 to '62, we also issued leas:es on this land for the sole purposeof getting fast uranium production. Outside of the Uravan Mineral Belt th.ere were also some exploration programs which were financed by- the A. E. C., which in general was truly exploration drilling.page 3
 R:They went out to try- to find productive horizons, and if youbump into an ore body, so much. the better. But there they were drilling for geologic informati.on. Here, first of all, they were drilling to really find uranium, and then the program as it pro-gressed was:-:--..,.the emphasis; was changed to drilling for information. W.et:11 o.e pleased if we hit an ore body but we're not displeased if we don"t.Do you have any· idea how large the exploration program was before 1951?No, but this is a matter of record. I mean, you're talking about dollars or .•. ?Number of men in the field . . .Number of men in the field? This information, I think, is easily avai.lable. Some of this stuff will come in these--might be in these early reports, yearly reports. Now, I wasn't in the explor- ati.on division ever, so I: can't speak with authority on this.You mentioned that the A.E.C. contracted in--it sponsored programs in exploration. Were these under contracts to companies? Do you have any idea of the names. of some of these companies? Were they large or small?Oh, they were large companies, Craig and Henwood; names in the bus:ines.s. Joy Manufacturing Company, for example, set up a specialG:R:G:R:G:R:page 4
 R: drilling company here for a time. They had beautiful drilling equipment out there. Boles Brothers out of Salt Lake did a great deal of exploration drilling. Minerals Engineering here in Grand Junction was very active in the Uravan Mineral Belt. I think that Ch.:ri.stians:on, the diamond bit people had equipment out but they didn"t have their own drilling company. They were in the background. There were a large number of independents with--some of them withone. rig, some of them numbers that could bid in on smaller jobs and take sub.....contracts~G: liow large was private exploration at this time? Do you have any idea?R: In the early day-sit was just darn near negligible. I suspect that the first company- that really got into doing much drilling was Union Carbide which was then U. S. Vanadium.G: Do you have any· idea why Union Carbide didn't stake more claims or attempt to work the uranium even though the Union Mines Survey was done by their subsidiary?R: Well no, except that-.,,...re.alize that it was a fairly conservative organization for a fact. Even now, they don't go out and blanket an area with mining claims because they always feel that it will cost them a hundred dollars a claim in assessment work. You and I as· individuals might go out and stake four or five claims someplacewhere we think therets some potential and we may or may not do a hundred dollars worth of assessment work because the only reason-- the only time you get into trouble in not doing it is if somebodypage 5
 R: jumps you. The government has never voided a mining claimbecause of failure to do as.ses.sment work. But Carbide feelsthat they have to do it every time on every claim. S.o, if they stake a thousand claims, there's a hundred thousand bucks that they have to spend on the thing. Well, it costs them more hundreds of thousands of dollars to spend that hundred thousand, you see. So they are quite cautious. Their land policies are quite conser- vative. If they think the property is worthwhile, they'll holdit. If they don't, theytll drop it.G: During th.e years the A.E.C. contracted with the U.S.V.C. and the V.C.A. t:'O purchase uranium concentrates from them, was there any parti.cular reason why they purchased it directly from them, rather than purchasing the ore from the miners?R: Because U.S.V.C. and V.C.A. had the mills. Now at the time the business--the industry started making its first few faltering steps. here, the only mill that was. running was Carbide's old mill at Rifle, and it was running strictly on ore from the Rifle Mine to produce vanadium. But there is uranium in that roscoelite.So, it's: a fairly simple and straightforward proposition to go ahead and put in a vanadium circuit at Rifle. V.C.A. has exper- ienced, because of its vanadium, its foothold on the vanadium market, and they undertook to take over the old A.S. and R. plant site at Durango. They had the buildings and they were vanadiumproducers and therets not much difference between producing uranium and vanadium, especially when we're working with an orepage 6
 R: that contains both. And so, these were the first two plants that could tool up and produce. Uravan was--there had been a planton w.nat is now the Uravan site, but mostly an operation, and I don't even know if there was any plant there. There was in the middle twenties, I know, but I think that it had probably been cut.,...,......torn down because at that time all they were interested in was- radium. The next plant that went in was our government plant at Monti.cello, which the A.E.C. built. It was the third plantG:to go into operation. The reason for starting with U.S.V. and V.C.A. was because they could produce first.Strictly a business proposition?R: Strictly--they were quite desperate, remember. A lot of peoplein Washington making the decisions and involving the expenditure of billions of dollars and the burning question was, 'Where the dickens are we going to get the feed materials.' Now the people out here in the West wei::e beating the drums for domestic--a few people like Oppenheimer and some other folks that really should know., kept saying that, 'You'll have to get your uranium overseas.We don't have any.' Th.ere was considerable difference when you're looking at a time when you need uranium, which way you're going to go. Now, if you're going to go overseas, you just spend money because you got to subsidize. everything. Over here, it is possible to get industry into the act. Remember, all we provided thesepeople was a market. We didn't build the plants, we didn't under- write bonds or a number of things we didn't do.page 7
 G: During this period when the A.E.C. was buying its concentrate from u.s.v.c. and V.C.A., many of the small miners felt theyw.ere cheated and blamed it on the government because of the in- accurate-..-like ore sampling.R: Letts face it, sampling was inaccurate in the early days. Uranium is. a heterogeneous ore. The miners have a lot of problems because they don't have a nice homogeneous mass to go in there and take it all out and have a good feel for the grade of material you'remining. Some. of them are mining little thin seams of a few inches, some of them got a few feet, but within the ore body itself therei.s: a w-ide variances. There are nice spots of high grade ore here, and surrounded by a halo of real marginal ore. Some of the stuff that looks like ore isn't ore. Consequently, when you take a load or a lot of ore, they got a hundred and fifty tons of this hetero- gene.ous mixture and you crush it, and you run it by yourself on a conveyor belt, you're getting high grade, low grade, high grade, low grade and the sample has to be taken correctly to get yourself atrue picture of what the total value of that whole lot is. In theold days, they sampled the stuff by hand. Now this has inherent inaccuracies, and what most ore producers don't like to admit is that the inherent inaccuracies generally tend to favor the miner. The old sampling plants .were crμde compared to the ones that they use today. Now usually, Union Carbide takes four separate samples.They take a first sample, then they take a percentage cut of that sample,.and they'll take a percentage cut of a third sample--or of a second sample and finally they take a percentage cut of a thirdpage 8
 R:sample. So they've got--by the time they get down to thefourth sample, maybe they're got a sample which represents onlya pound of the ton of material that they put in originally. But the original cut that they took out of there represented maybe two hundred pounds. A ten percent cut, a ten percent cut, ten percent cut--till you get down to the one. But this is a pretty fair sample because a ten percent cut, they're taking quite a--they're getting that sample bucket, that sample wheel is going through that stream of ore fairly rapidly. And it's getting both the highgrade and the low grade.Did the A.E.C. have any control over this ore salilPling?Oh yes, and we exercised it. For one thing, the A.E.C. had astake in it. Because in the early days the cost of uranium con- centrate was fairly well tied to the cost of ore as well as thecost of producing the concentrate. The cost of the ore was direct- ly tied into the operation of the miner's operation. A good samplewas fair to all. A poor sample hurt somebody. But if the poor sample hurt the miner, he quit mining. If the poor sample hurt the miller, the cost of uranium went up, so we were by-in-large quite interested. The Cormnission financed two surveys of sampling.One was by the Colorado School of Mining, the other by a research foundation, as I recall. It discovered and they brought to light that practices could be improved, equipment could be added, and I think had a great deal to do with improving the quality of theG:R:sampling. We ourselves have a sampling check program. Bill Anderson,page 9
 R:the fellow you met earlier, used to run around the country with truckloads of ore and we'd sample it at Monticello where we felt we had one of the better samplers. We would go tosomebody's mill and say, 'Okay here's--we want you to sample this lot of ore.' We'd run it through their sampler, and then run back to Monticello and sample it again. By the time you had gonethrough all these things, you had it pretty well mixed. You probably could have gone in and sampled it with a teaspoon andcome out with a fairly accurate sample. But also we could tell these people whether it was high or low or hereabouts. So we ran these-,,--oh, every mill got hit at least twice a year and they were cautious about it. They didn't like to be--I mean, they wanted to be close, they didn't want to have us jumping onto them because theyhad a low sample and they didn't want the management jumping onto them because it would be a high sample. We found that the poor sampling practices, in general, hurt them, hurt the mill.What way did it hurt the mill?Well, their samples were higher than normal, than they should have been. They were inaccurate on the high side so that the mill-- the miners got a few cents a pound more for his ore than it was really worth. It's long been my opinion that the poor sampling practice in the early days contributed significantly to the lower mill recoveries that they had. They were actually recoveringbetter percentages than they thought they were because their mill heads were artificially high. Now the only reason the poor samplingG:R:page 10
 R:practices,to me,penalized the miller is that in uranium, th values are usually in the finer material. The coarser material is more likely to be barren, and poor samplers will take thefines and the coarse material will bounce out. If you're shovel sampling it's easier--if you got a shovel in your hand, you know it's a lot easier to shovel up fine stuff than it is to shovel up rocks four inches in diameter or even three inches in diameter, and if you get a few six inch diameter rocks, you're not going to shovel those out, although those are the ones that tend to average out the grade because they're there and they should be sampled.The only time that the sample that gets predominant fines hurts the miners by the fact that most of the moisture is also in the fines, you see, so you get a bigger moisture count. But, the moisture I don't think is really a significant factor in this country where it's arrid and most bf the material that comes out of the mine is pretty darn dry!You mentioned the contracts with the V.C.A. and the U.S.V.C. that the A.E.C. negotiated for this concentrate. What basis were these contracts negotiated on, cost-plus or . . . ?There were two types. There were no cost-plus. The reactionto the old War Department cost-plus contracts had already hitthe government. So what you had was a formula. You took your audited cost of milling plus your audited costs of ore acquisition,the two variables were actual. Say it cost you five dollars a pound per pound of U-308 put into the mill to mill it, and you got a 90 percent recovery, so you came out with four and a half pounds.G:R:pag 11
 R: Then it cost you roughly four dollars and a half a pound forth.at U-308 when you bought it from the miner or if you produced it. Th.en, you're up to about nine dollars per pound of cost and then they would contract for a fixed profit. I mean, you couldn'tvary the profit by doing anything to the recovery or what haveyou. You've got a fixed profit. Its cost plus fixed fee isreally what it is, except that the formula was employed for the purpose that as changes in technology drove costs down, the govern- ment participated. Then the formula was reduced so then theprice went down. Now really what this was,was a guaranteed price ~or concentrate. The miner had a guaranteed price for ore, sothe miller was now getting a guarantee and price for his con- centrate. Then the government did just what the governmentusually does when it wants something bad, and that is, plantswere amortized on a five year basis, not ten or twenty; they got these so-called rapid write-offs, which is very advantageous.G: When the--when the V.C.A. and U.S.V.C. overestimated the valueof the ore or the content of the ore, they were really losing then?R: Costs went up--cost us, too, see. Their price went up, the price that we paid them for the concentrate, but their profit didn't go up.G:R:G:So they actually lost money. You lost . . .It cost us the formula--it cost the taxpayers.But actually in the long run on that basis the miner didn't lose too much because he was guaranteed his price.page 12
 R: Yeah. Well, if the miner was actually short-changed, he lost. In all the numbers of transactions that have occurred there has to have been people that lost. We all, including government, were accused of short-changing the miner.G:R:What was the other type of contract that was worked out?Well, flat--flat price. In the early days it was almost impossible to get anyone to agree to a flat price because, man, there were just too many variables. The ore grade varied a great deal. You could design a plant that was, say, going to operate at best at,say the ore containing twenty-five hundredths uranium. But there were no guarantees that three years or two years or five yearsdown the road that you were still going to get your twenty-five hundredths ore at that point. The metalurgical characteristics might not change to a point where your chemical consumption would be much greater. It seems that--and this isn't a rule of thumb-- but it seems that every designer I've ever talked to always claimed his greatest problem arose because the type of ore that he designed the mill for failed to show up when the mill was built and putinto operation.Did they have this trouble with the mill at Monticello?Well, the mill at Monticello was more or less--it wasn't an experimental mill--it was a production type mill. But we tried things. That's where pressure leaching was first tried. That'sG:R:where iron exchange was first tried. That's where solvent extractionpag 13
 R: was first tried on a production size mill. We had the first car- bonate leach with pressure leaching for example. We did a lotof things. That mill was either being modified or had just been modified all the time. We had two circuits. That was the first mill that had two circuits so we could process both high lime ores or low lime ores. It had a vanadium circuit in it, just likethe mills at Durango and Rifle and Uravan.G: Speaking of vanadium, why do you think the government was paying also for the vanadium content of the ore? Was the government ... ?R: Just to get the ore. The miners had been selling that ore. The miners had been selling that ore to private buyers for its vanadium values. You couldn't expect them (this is Ritter speaking) to sell that ore to somebody for government use of uranium and look over the vanadium values that they knew were there. Just like the precious metal producers, if they've got g!Dld and silver in their ore, they want to get paid for both. And you can't blame them,because they're both useful and valuable commodities. Vanadium and uranium are both a useful and valuable commodity. Actually, I realize that one of the reasons for the government putting the floor under the vanadium was that when you increase the uraniumproduction--when you increase the vanadium production you increase the uranium production. What did you do, you've created a surplus of vanadium. So we had a stockpile of vanadium here for quite awhile. Here around this compound. Because we bought vanadium, we paid for vanadium in the ore we bought and produced vanadium in ourpage 14
 R: mill at Monticello. We bought vanadium from Climax, from V.C.A., and from U.S.V. whenever they needed a market, when theconnnercial market wouldn't take care of their production. We got quite a bit of it. Otherwise these--vanadium would have been a glut on the market. U.S.V. and V.C.A. as far as their operations out here were not uranium producers. They thought they were vanadium producers. I don't think they'd have been reall happy to glut the market in their own specialty.G: Do you think that also might have influenced U.S.V.C. in not seeking uranium claims--their feeling that they were a vanadium producer first?R: I don't think so. Of course, this is--I'm second guessing.G: Okay.R: They're a·fter--if they can see a dollar, they'11 do it. Maybe it's if they can see a hundred dollars maybe they'll do it. Maybe it's a million dollars, several million. But they're very careful about what they do and the fact that they've been out here for a long time is one thing. I know that the currentmanagement says, 'And we're going to be out here for a lot longer.' See? So that they're, I think what I'm saying is that they're looking at whatever action that they take, what effect is it going to have upon them in ten years or twenty years, or thirty years.When we're dead and gone and our children are running this operation, let's not build in any problems for them.pag 15
 G: Okay, when the program changed, the program of procurement in1 51, do you think it was a combination of things which changed?R: What changes do you have particularly in mind?G: Well, when they raised the price. Prior to that the price has been much lower on the earlier circulars.R: They weren't getting enough uranium. To get enough uranium, you pay a little more and more people will go out and look for it. Also, when you pay a little more, this means that the miner can mine the lower grade uranium. The mills found they could produce more uranium with a lower grade of mill feed.G: During this period do you think that . . .R: It's my personal opinion that the original prices on uranium were pretty chintzy.G: During this early period when do you think the A.E.C. changed their opinion about the reserves on the Colorado Plateau?R: Well, it wasn't until '50, '51. And I don't think the A.E.C. dared to have much of an opinion in the early days. They were being told. The A.E.C. was brand new, so they went out and they hired brains and they listened to the seers and the experts and they heard a variety of opinions. I've talked to Howard Balsey and you have too, probably, about his problems in going back toWashington and the only sympathetic ears he got were the ears of the Congressmen and Senators from Colorado and Utah.page 16
 G:R:The A.E.C., this was more or less told by Washington officials what to do?The A.E.C. were Washington officials. Let's fact it, these are bureaucrats. They hired people with nuclear help--knowledge. But they're dog-goned few, darned few experts in the field of uranium raw materials and those few experts there were, were divided in their opinion.So the few who worked out here didn't seem to change their minds really until that period?That's right. I think that's correct. Because you read that copy of that hearing I provided you with this morning, and you'll see that they're finally starting to admit that there is uranium outon the Western United--or in the United States. Not confined to the West, although this is the only place we've produced it so far. There is uranium out here, and they're finally agreeing that it's simply a matter of the extent of the effort. But I don't think--I mean, I think that--it's been my personal opinion all along that the original, the early releases and circulars were just token releases and circulars so that nobody could point the finger at them and say, 'Look you so and so's, you're doingnothing but subsidize the South Africa and Canadian uranium producers. You're doing nothing for the Americans.'Just sort of keeping the American market alive?G:R:G:R: Yeah. And if it's there, why somebody will probably come along.pag 17
 G:B:Okay, well, thanks. I'm finished wit~ my early period questions.You mentioned that once a body of land had been identified as an ore bearing body, the A.E.C., or pardon me, the government would withdraw this from the public domain and the A.E.C. would rent a lease on it? What were the qualifications for obtaining an A.E.C. lease on this?Well, they were quite general; the guideline was that the A.E.C. wanted early uranium production. So that what they were lookingfor was people with the financing, the know-how, and the ability, either the equipment or the ability to get the equipment, andthe people to get in there and start sinking or driving at it, getting that uranium and start producing it. They wanteduranium from these leases yesterday!Then this was the sole factor that determined who got the lease?When I came to work for the Commission, they told me, 'Man, Ritter, the next year and a half in this business is critical. We've got to get every pound of uranium we can get.' And you know that kept going on the the next five years. Every year,'Man, the next year and a half are critical!' There was--we kept-- I wasn't involved in the leasing program in those days but couldn't help being aware of it, because it was administered out of this office, out of the division I was in. They were continuallyhammering. We got--every time there was additional capacity developing in a mill, somebody was modifying their mill so theyR:B:R:page 18
 R: could get more production through it. But the first thing they could think of was, 'Okay, let's get another A.E.C. lease goingso that we can use that productive capacity in this mill.' Remember that the A.E.C. kept its fingers on the production tothe extent that they told the leaser where to deliver his ore.He was told to bring it here over to Monticello, deliver it to Durango, deliver it to Uravan, and this was strictly becausethese people at these mill locations said that we can handle another fifty tons a day. The Commission publicized this leas- ing program fairly diligently in the area, trying to interest as many companies with proven experience as they could. As Irecall they had a listing of several hundred individuals. and companies that were interes·ted. Now, some of these people say, like some of the big copper producers said, 'Well, we're only interested in multi-thousand or multi-hundred thousand ton ore bodies.' Joe Dokes was interested in an ore body where he could get in and make something better than wages. He didn't have millions of dollars to spend developing an ore body. He wanted to be able to get in there and start from a rim and start producing practically from the day- that he first put a drill hole in there. There was a variance in the type of land--in the tracts that we had available. Some of them had drilled out ore bodies. Pure and simple there it was. There was enough drill holes in it to say this is an ore body. Others had drill holes in ore, but is it an ore body? So these leasers were really leasing a tract that hads.ome ore in it. It had mostly potential. Now the first leasespag 19
 R:B:that went out were the ones that had ore bodies. Maybe theywere small ore bodies, but they were there and they could be had.So let's get cracking!You mentioned that the A.E.C. was mostly interested in getting companies that had experience in this field. I noticed in the1955 hearings that one of the small miners in the area hadalleged that the Golden Cycle, Barkley and Company and the WortmeyerMining Company had no experience in uranium mining. Do you think this was true?Yes, I do. How many of these companies had e}.."'Perience in uranium mining, really? There were two: V.C.A. and U.S.V.C. There werea lot of individuals that had experience. Most of the leases, remember,went to partnerships and joint ventures which were composed of experienced individuals. Shaddock-Den, the small independentwas one of the companies, mining companies without previous uranium mining experience. The Golden Cycle whose previous experience was in general--the bulk of their experience was in gold. They were gold mining operators. But they were a miner and they had other mining operations. Those were really the only two outfits thatyou could call out and out mining companies whose scope of operation was in other metals besides uranium that ever got leases.Once the large companies would get the lease, many times they would sub-contract those, correct?R:B:R: Right.page 20
 B:A man by the name of Schumacher in these hearings posed the question, 'Why then didn't the A.E.C. grant these leases to the small miner, the independent miner, inasmuch as they were doing the bulk of the work, why weren't they getting the leases rather than the large companies?' Do you have any . ?Yeah, I think I know the answer, and it still wouldn't satisfyJohn Schumacher. The answer was that it was an incentive to gettT.. S. V. and V. C. A. , these are the operators he was talking about,to expand the mills. The A.E.C. in effect said, 'If you will put in another X hundred tons per day capacity into your mill, we will lease you this land which you can develop into a producer that will provide this X hundreds of pounds of additional ore.' They would just trade, the A.E.C. was trading its land to that mill operator to get that yellow cake into the can. They gained two says. They were getting the yellow cake in the can, the primary objective, but they were also getting a royalty from the mill operator.As of 1955, there have been forty-nine leases granted and thirty-four of them were in effect. But yet there were three hundred applications. I wonder why had there been so few leases granted during this periodof time?We're not interested in creating a situation of overproduction. By and large, there are two schools of thought here. The government spent some money, so much money drilling these withdrawn lands. We got investments. We as taxpayers have an investment in thisR:B:R:pag 2
 R: withdrawn land. One school of thought is, 'Okay, let's getthese lands under lease, get the ore produced, they the royaltythat the government gets, they'll pay us back for this investment.' The other school of thought says, 'Oh, don't do that. Thisuranium in the ground out here in Uravan Mineral Belt is likemoney in the bank. Don't touch your capital. Wait until an emergency comes up and you really need it. Then is the time toget it. Don't trade off your birthright--what you have now forthe fast buck.' There are two schools of thought and they'vefought it out steady, and still are. But my original answer Ithink still goes that the Commission was in no way interested in creating a production surplus. If the mills could handle additional ore, and they couldn't get it from private people, then go outB:R:with another lease. Now, also, there was considerable agitation from people who felt that mining leases, A.E.C. leases,were just a guaranteed income. This wasn't the case a hundred percent. Itwas the case most of the time. If it hadn't been, you wouldn't have the competition for the leas.es.In many articles on the leasing program, it's said that after 1955 the government was interested in getting out of what they callwithdrawal leasing. Now what is meant by withdrawal leasing?Well, that is leasing the lands on the--leasing the lands that were withdrawn from public entry. See, we're getting--phasing into this business of, into this idea that the ore that we know is in our withdrawn land, let's keep it for the time that we need,page 22
 R:really have an emergency and need a lot or uranium in a hurry. Also, there's always the private enterprise concept we ' ve got to support. I have to support it, we have to support it, and that isthat private industries whould run this business because any time that the government is involved as intimately as it was in the forties and fifties and early sixties in this program, it cost you money. There's administration involved. So, if you get down to the point where the government is simply buying, just being the purchaser of the products that it needs, this is a role of govern- ment that is universal. The De£ense Department, Commerce, the Interior, everybody has needs and they buy what they need.Once a miner of a mining company had obtained one of these A.E.C. leases, what did this promise him in terms. of future stability?He had a market for, usually, specified quantities of ore, starting in the middle fifties, that in general ran through the term. The leases original terms were five year leases and then they were renewable at the option of the Commission, and they were in fact all renewed, any lessee that wanted to renew his lease had his lease renewed. But he got a guaranteed price and he really didn'thave to compete quite as hard as his neighbor who was producing ore from the public domain on an unpatented mining claim becaus.e I think that the mills were treating this leasor almost the same as their own. Maybe he had a higher priority. I've had people from U.S.V. say that if you've got too much ore, we'll cut back. We won't cutB:R:the A.E.C. leasers back. Now late in the fifties and early sixties,pag 23
 R:this wasn't the case. The major producers on the A.E.C. leases were upon Atkinson Mesa and they were cut back. But earlier thanthat the A;E.C. leases were fairly well, if they could convinceour leas.ing branch that they had to produce 'X' hundred pounds per month more, they probably got it and the mill operator would follow through on it without quibbling. But if you and I were out there mining in Joe Doke's was:h, and we found our ore body was a little bit bigger or thicker then we had expected, and we could producean extra hundred and fifty tons a month,maybe we could produce that, or maybe we could sell that and maybe we couldn't, depending on how badly the mill wanted the ore.The advantages of an A. E. C. lease weire fairly obvious. Were there any hidden disadvantages?Yeah, you had the government looking down your throat. Which is always a problem. You couldn't get away with the sloppy mining practices that you could if you were operating on your own property. The A.E.C. leases were the first ones that were forced to ventilate to reduce radiation levels in the mines. The A.E.C. leases werethe first operations that were shut down until they got their radiation levels down. I remember that, in general, maybe it was more nuisance than anything else. When you're working for the government, you will, as a contractor, you will pay more attention to the requirements of other agencies, Department of Labor, BureauB:R:of Mines, than if you're not a government contractor.page 24
 B: Okay. Could we take a short recess?R: Certainly.B:R:You mentioned that one of the problems of having an A.E.C. lease was, as you say, having the government breathing down you neck,and the miners had to install these fans in the mines. When did they first start cracking down on this, on these safety regulations?Golly, they got going on it fairly early. We had a man working with radiation and ventilation in '54. You should talk to Stan Meyer about this. Now he wasn't that man that was working in '54, but he took his place and he is the local 'memory' on the earlyradiation working, you know. Remember now, we had primitive equip- ment, th~ radiation detection apparatuses were--I mean, you could go in with a geiger counter or scintillator. That didn't tell you a hell of a lot because normal background of the mine was enoughto throw everything off the scale, you see, of the sensitive instru- ments. But the docemeters and the early counters, the alpha counters and what have you, weren't as good as they are now. They had strains and problems. But they could tell you how many MRs an hour you hadin a certain working place and I'm sure Mr. Meyer has worksheets and can give you examples on some of the things that happened. Radiation-- so this is one of the reasons that I'm not real concerned aboutsome of these low level hazards that exist here in Grand Junctionand elsewhere, because I know from personal experience what tremendous amounts of radiation the early miners worked in for weeks and monthspage 25
 R:on end, you know. And they didn't all die!G:R:B:R:Not all of them.If you were a uranium miner and you didn't smoke, you're longevity was about as good as anybody's:. If you were a uranium miner and did smoke, you had it!Some of the uranium miners of the early fifties claim that the A.E.C. was incompetent; that they didn't have, quote, 'A feel forthe uranium business.' To what extent do you agree or disagree with this?Well, I think that most of the people that were involved in the early days were competent in their speciality. They had geologists, they had engineers,they hired mineralologists, et cetera. But remember how--that they were practically--that the only peoplethat had competence in the narrow specialized field of uranium- vanadium ore were under contract or were employed by U.S.V. or V.C.A. Now we used consultants and there were a few people likeDick Fisher, uranium-vanadium geologists for the U.S.G.S. andthey were here. Now I recall I was around, before I went to work for the Commission, I was in meetings at Moab and in Denver inwhich the A.E.C. was roundly castigated for being insensitive, incompetent, you name it. I would tend to discourage the idea that incompetence was rampant. I would certainly tend to agreewith the idea that people were willing to try almost anything. The fact of the matter remains that the old way of doing things couldn'tpage 26
 R:be continued. We had to change, there had to be changes, andthe changes are certainly not satisfactory to all and sundry.The only changes that were really satisfactory were the guarantees . Now, I think in the early days that there was a feeling that the A.E.G. wanted to run the mining operations. I can't subscribeto this feeling at all because in order to do this, we wouldhave had to create a bureaucracy which would have almost floundered by its own weight. We were bad enough, and if we were old line agency, it would have been worse. But the fact of the matter1.is, I'd say ninety-five percent--maybe ninety percent of the people out here that went to work for the A.E.C. in the Raw Materials Program were people without prior government experience. We did some of the darndest things! Things that no old line agency would have been caught dead doing. Some of them worked, and some of them didn't. Most of them worked to some extent.You may have already answered this question, but just for my benefit, we're rehashing it over. Why did the A.E.C. find it necessary tore-evaluate its uranium ore purchasing policy in 1951?Because the volume of uranium being produced was not adequate.Is it possible that the arms race, the Soviet nuclear threat, and the war with Communist powers, in Korea, had anything to do with it?Yeah, I think yes, it did. The fact of the matter is, I think that our intelligence said that the Soviets were getting closer to nuclear bombs, to a nuclear capability. I think they had the bomb, didn'tB:R:B:R:pag 27
 R:they, in '51? It was. during Truman's administration that they exploded the first one. We know the experience of having thebomb, or a bomb or maybe five bombs didn't give you control ofthe United States, but man, it'd really give you a jump. You had to have a lot of bombs in order to have a real deterrent force. Remember, we were in the age of the deterrent force in those days. But we simply had to get the nuclear materials for the Department of Defense. Now we had gone, taken giant strides down the chain past the uranium processing mills here on the Plateau, in the refineries and in the gaseous diffusion plants and in the plutonium plants, that's where the big money is~-you know, billions and billions of dollars. Those people were well on the way, and they were running Oak Ridge, recycling low grade time after time because they had the equipment there and they had the power con- tracted for, they had to use the power, and so they were just keeping operating on anything they had. In the late forties andin the early fifties, they were even considering bringing inuranium tailings from Europe, not to put them in these concentrators here, as we know them out here, but in the feed material plants because they could get a little bit of uranium out of them andthey had the capacity which wasn't being used.When the United States finally realized that they did have a much larger ore reserve right here in the United States than they had known before, what effect did this have on the ore buying policy? In other words, buying, purchasing ore from the Congo and from Canada?B.:Page 28
 R: There were no concentrate, foreign contracts negotiated, Ithink, after 1956. rtm guessing on this date, but that's close. It was in October of 1957 that the announcement was made here that current and existing contracts were more than adequate to meet our defense needs. Now, remember, we had existing contracts in South A frica, A ustralia, and Canada, and the United States, which the government honored. Now the government stretched out its deliveries, its purchases from the Canadian government. Not a long stretch-out like we got from domestic producers, but they did stretch it out. But tb.ey couldn't do much with the South African which got up to a maximum of about six thousand tons a year. They ran that out fairly close to the contract. The Australians never had a big operation going and that ended in a normal circumstance. But by 1960 we were still getting some concentrate in considerable volume from Canada. It was in '64,I think, that the last vanadium concentrate came in. But the government never really cut back on domestic purchases of the concentrate until about in 1964 when we started the stretch-out, when the stretch-out contracts really became effective. Then we cut--what we did was cut back the yearly volume in return for an extended market through 1970. Have I answered your question?B: Yes. As a means of summation, can you discuss the effect of the incentives, or rather the circulars had on the overall mining operations in the Colorado Plateau?R: Well, I'll reiterate what I said earlier. I think that these incentives were the whole base for the development of the domesticpage 29
 R:industry. Before that, i.t just didn't pay, because before1948, there was a market for vanadium and it was a fluctuating market. There was a market for radium and this, too, wasn'ta steady demand. The market for radium was low because theprice of radium was so darned high. Uranium as such had to bethe dominant mineral that you wanted. I think the law of supplyand demand had to be met. The supply was there, although wedidn't know about it in '48, the demand was there. So if youcreate enough incentives for people to get out and go, they'll create the supply. This is what you had to do. If I had it todo over again, I just wouldn't have been quite so slow in comingout with a price that these miners could live with. Because the difference between a buck and a half for twenty-hundredths oreand three and a half for twenty-hundredths or three and a half a pound, is only two bucks, and when you get down the chain thattwo dollars per pound isn't a heck of a lot of money. It's not being compounded. It's a one time purchase, a one time expend_iture, and having it when you need it is of a fair amount of importance.One final thing. Could you jus.t give us an explanation of your position here at the compound and your experience in the uranium industry prior to this?My initial experience in the uranium industry was as branch manager for a mining equipment house operating out of Denver. In my territory, I had all of Colorado, Eastern Utah, Northern New Mexico, and South Dakota, and Wyoming. Now these encompass all of the earlyB:R:page 30
 R:uranium producing areas. In 1952 the price of lead went to pot, and my markets for equipment in the base metal industries just evaporated and so I was forced to devote almost all of my timeto this brand new uranium mining industry. So I got out here in 1951, '52 and '53. I got a pretty good overview of the area.I knew where the mines were because I was there unloading equip- ment as fast as I could. I left this company early in '53 and went to work for Garwood and Gerlach who were the leasers on Charley Steen's property, the Mi Vida. I took over as chief engineer and superintendant, combined title,just about the time they holed into the ore bodies, from the downhill side of the bre body. I worked there for several months and then came to work for the Commission in mid '53. I worked as an examining engineer under the initial Production Bonus Program, Circililar Six, for about a year. Then they created a title of 'Staff Engineer' in the ore buying section, and I was it, the section under staff engineer for some months.They finally decided that since the government was actually buying crude ore it should be doing the contracting and not be contractor. So we set me up as a section, and I got four engineers all at once and we started writing contracts and buying ore in Monticello andMarysville, and I think it was Grants, the first three locations that we were operating out of. This section later developed into the ore buying branch and we had as high as nine buying pointsoperating at one time. We had at one time over six hundred ore purchase contracts. Oh, it was coming in all over. Since 1958 I have been in this division, and my prime purpose has been in thepag 31
 R: administration of the mill contracts as they applied to custom ore purchases and ore acquisition in general. This is phasing out at the end of this year. So that's a thumb nail sketch. I've been a Branch Chief since '58.B: Thank you very much, Mr. Ritter.G: Thank you."page 32