   JERR Y ANDERSON Salt Lake City, Utah Tape No. 80An interview by Patricia Ray June 23, 1970American West Center University of Utah Uranium History Series
 Table of ContentsBackground.Experiences in Marysvale. . .Explorations by Fathers and Sons.Claims. . ... • Inner Feelings Towards Methods of Prospecting.•120 26 27 31
 The following is an interview with Jerry Anderson, conducted by Patricia Ray on June 23, 1970.R:A:"Mr. Anderson, how did you become interested in the Uranium Industry?My father was a well driller and he drilled wells for anyone that needed water and usually that was farmers and he had to go to quite remote areas to drill his wells, you know, and he was in the desertcountry up into the mountains. At that time and in the 35's and in the 40's, the farmers were really going to town growing crops and things for the wars that were about to go on, so at any rate, he moved out from Nevada in '37, I believe, and moved up north into Utah, drilling wells and so he had quite a knowledge on different formations of the earth and a different, oh, formations and what they stood for and different sandstones and clay formations and things like that. So,he educated himself and I would supposeyou would call him a self-made geologist, by digging into the earth like that. But he always had in mind that there was an easier way to make money than drilling wells for farmers and things, although it kept him out of the service during the second World War. At any rate, in the early or the late 40's and early SO's is when they started really getting interested in uranium in that country and so he was alittle tired of drilling wells, like I said, and he had offers from people in California to find these uranium properties and stake them and sell them to different people from out of state--usually Californiabecause California people heard of the uranium boom and we were setting
 A:right where it was happening. So my father started to learn how to fly a small private plane and after a few months he got his license and he would fly over the Colorado Plateau and around Green River and Moab and where the uranium activity was going on.We would fly with a scintaillator or a neucleometer geiger counter and we would fly right down into the canyon real close and when wewould pick up radio activity we would have our bags of lime or different colorations of powder we would take with us and we would just drop it right at the site that we would get the count from.Then we would go in later with jeeps and trucks and whatever vehicles that it took to get in on the property and stake the claims and some of the finds that we found (it appeared that they were good) so wewent ahead and staked a few for ourselves. But in the meantime hehe was selling these claims to a few people who wanted to buy them from out of state as an investment because there were two or three people during that time that really strμck it rich. One of them that I did remember was Charley Steen and there was a Mr. Pick that struck it rich and I mean they struck it like millions of dollars worth of uranium and their veins of ore were fabulous and this is what every-body was trying to find was a 20 foot vein of high grade uranium and vanadium so you wouldn't have to work any more in your life. At any rate, through prospecting like we did by air and jeep we found some pretty strikes and so we formed our own corporation, my father did.I was only sixteen at the time, sixteen or seventeen, so I was justpage 2
 A: kind of along to help out, but any rate, my father organized a corporation with his cousin around twenty-five of our uraniumclaims that was real good and he called it the Magnolia Lead Cor- poration. They raised enough money from this claim (at that timethe government was giving a bonus of ten thousand dollars for certain claims that showed a high grade uraniuni) and with the 10 thousand dollars they went out and bought, at least put a down payment on the necessary equipment to go ahead and start mining that. Am I going too fast for you?R: Ah, no.A: After buying the necessary equipment to mine uranium, they started digging tunnels to follow the vein, it looked good. Some days theore showed a real high count. I forget the percentage now. This has been done so long ago. I know that it didn't take long to buy some real nice equipment to go ahead and do it up right like it should be done. We was going along there real fine for about six months, buy- ing new equipment and then all of a sudden the whole face of the sand- stone cliff that we were blasting off was empty and barren of any radioactivity and it was from this day forward that my dad thought that there must be another lode of uranium someplace, someplace onthat Colorado Plateau but it surely wasn't there where we've been digging for so many months, and we used to find that uranium in old fossilized trees, in old fossilized dinosaur bones. For some reason these absorbed radioactivity. Now, I'm no geologist, but I'm sure
   A: the geologists these days could explain this but I still can't.So my father was always looking for Mother lode. It must havecome from the center of the earth like most Mother lode depositsof ore does. So we continued searching for the uranium on that Colorado Plateau, over by the Temple Mountain and the Henry Mountain area and at least fifty miles from Emery in all directions, at least southeast of Emery, the city of Emery,look~ng for Mother lode or a great deposit of uranium then we find after we'd dig for awhile andwe'd come up with a disappointing find and no more ore. So, while flying in that country in the light plane my father had we found some of these extrusions of, oh, volcanic intrusions. It's like, it was like big dikes. It wasn't a volcano coming out from one point of theearth but it was like you took mud in your hand and you squeezed it thro_ugh your fingers and that's the·appearance that these dikes or thevolcanic extrusions have upon the earth seeing it from the air, andthese dikes,which range from anywhere from two inches wide to fiftyfeet wide sprang into the air like a China Wall with about'in some .instances they would go up as high as two or three hundred feet andit looked like someth~ng man would make,and by flying over· this countrywe noticed that it was some of the only ,volcanic action in that area and also by flying over with our delicate instruments we picked up radioactivity,more so than in the surrounding area and these dikes ran for thirteen miles in one direction and about three miles wide'the fingers of dikes and walls of this material. So we went back in by jeep and to further exploration we found that they, after assaying4
 A: some of the material we found that they contained about thirty different species of rare earth minerals and a small grade of uranium deposit in these dikes. They were made up of the hot volcanic intrusions that was not found any place else in that region that I know of and so this could be possibly a source ofthe Mother lode material. We had to find, we had to get a geologist and go out there with us to find for sure whether this would beworth further exploration. So we hired two geologists and one, I rem- ember, his name was Byron Davies from St. George, Utah, and we tookhim up on the property and flew him over the counb~y, showed him this igneous intrusion and showed him the samples, the assay reports, and the whole works and he said that the Atomic Energy, three years before our find on that, had the same idea and that they had set aside that property there that we had found as a possible site for further explor- ation for uranium. But in the meantime, people were finding so muchof the ore, the uranium, in that area that the Atomic En~rgy really didn't need it for their explorations, so at least we were on theright track of the possibility. My ~.ather was quite a promoter, soit didn't take very long to raise, I think it was about fifty thousand dollars from the local towns people, and he formed another corporation.This time he called it the le Madre Corporation, the mother, and with these monies he was to stake the country and that means staking claims continuously of claims thirteen miles long and three miles wide andit all had to be staked. He couldn't just set it aside. Now to stake the claim you had to go, if I remember right, six hundred feet one way
    A: and fifteen hundred feet the other way and setting about four corner posts and then intermediate posts, with a claim marker on each claim. So this was quite an operation and so we set out tohire the necessary men and equipment to that job. In the meantime the stock that we had listed on the Salt Lake Stock Exchange went,was going up all the time cause people heard about it and they wanted in, and yet we sold as much stock as we thought we should. Therewas a lot of investors wanting to invest. So, well, we went ahead and staked this property. It was an undertaking of about one yearto take care of this obligation. Now while we're doing this, furtherknowledge of what was happening out there, · is of the mines that wasin that area producing h_igh grade uranium ore was a Mr. P:ic.k that I spoke of earlier and ah, he one year before that has sold part of his claim for I think, two and a half million dollars to some b_ig company. They gave him quite a size check for that portion of it and of course,he stayed on to continue working on the claims because he loved that -kind of work. At any rate he was only at a point six miles away from those igneous intrusions that we were talking about--six miles to theeast. He was in the country that was in the upheaval on the east side of the Plateau that went up and broke off, and he·was about a thousand feet lower than we were, into a different formation that contained uranium. So, if you can picture that, he was down in the area thatwas broken off and eroded away six miles to the east and we were back on the western slope up on top, a thousand feet higher than he was and this was the igneous intrusion that we're speaking of that we could6
 A: see visible from the surface of the earth. So we felt that aft r we staked the claim which took us a year and used up quite a bit ofthat money that we had raised to get thing started and we felt at least my father felt that to really understand whether there was uranium ore there or not, we had to bring in drilling machines and drill at least one hole a thousand feet to fifteen hundred feet, at least every half a mile down our claims for thirteen miles. Now,to drill a well that deep and as big around as have to go to takea scintillator reading it probably cost upwards of four of five dollars a foot. So, there's quite a few thousand feet of hole to drill. In the meantime my father was working quite hard and thisis a new challenge to him and a new undertaking and there was a lot of stress and strain on his part because he was the sole originator of this thing and the man that had to get everything in order and keep track of all the papers, all the claims, all the men that hehired to claim this part of the country, and to take care of those investors that had their money placed with him, and it was in 1955 that my father died. Of course, like I said, I was si~teen and I couldn't do too much with the operation that he had, and the people that he had with him kind of lost control of the whole thing aftermy father passed away and so at any rate, like I said, my father had the idea in mind that he had to drill those holes to find the ore and to prove to him and to the world that it was there, the motherlode in that area. But his thoughts and his plans and his ideas died with him because from that day forward nobody did anything about it.7
 A: It took a lot of money to take care of that and to get thoseholes drilled and the turmoil and all the fighting and bickering between all the other people and it never did gel and so just sixteen years ago, and you go up in that country and you ask them aboutwhat happened to that country and they say that it's still in litigation. The people fighting amo.ng themselves, the money thatwas lost and the money that people felt that was owed back to them and the possibility of striking it rich never did do anything. Ifeel myself that if someone was to go back there with the necessary mining tools to explore that, I'm sure that they would find the uranium that we were seeking during that time.R: Have you ever been back to look for .•. ?A: I have never been back. No, I moved to California shortly after, well, in 1955 because I had no job you might say and no interest there and no tie downs, so my wife and myself moved to California in '55 and since then we've been on our own doing ·the things that we wanted to do and I started in the ornamental iron business in, let's see, in '61, and we were going real strong in that now. I'm in partnership with my two brothers, it's a corporation now andwe're doing real well. We're moving the operation out to Or~nge County into a bigger operation, but like I say, I know that there is a mother lode of uranium in that country and I know it's right in that same location that we were exploring but it would take quite a few thousands of dollars to improve it and I suppose when the8
 A: government really needs the uranium that they will look for it--the Atomic Energy--cause they have the money behind them to do some- thing like that.R: Did your brothers prospect also?A: Yes, they were with me at the time. I have a brother that is thirteen months older than I am and I have one that's about four years younger. The younger one didn't do much except bring water to the workers but my older brother worked right along with me.R: You know, somebody bringing water to the workers--would this have ?to be brought from ....A: We were working out--do you want me to get rid of that?R: That's okay. It's not that bad.A: At any rate, we were working out of Emery, working those claims and we had I guess twenty people with us and we would--we brought horses. We found this is the best transportation to carry the stakes around with us and my brother headed up one crew of ten people with the transits and horses and jeeps and things, and I headed up the other crew and we would just go ahead and survey a line for thirteen miles.Now this was over just about any kind of terrain you've ever seen, anywhere from meadow country to high plateaus areas and then right down into chasms that broke off in that country sometimes a thousand foot or even fifteen hundred feet straight down. You'd be walking9
 A: along across the desert and you'd find a big crack in the earth and that would be where the upheaval was and exposed all these different formations. Now, I used to know all the different formations by heart, but I don't know them anymore, the different sandstones and the different formations that the uranium appeared in. Ye_ah,my brother and I were sent on an exploring trip one timebefore we found these intrusions and we had an old weapon's carrier and we were going across the desert about sundown and we couldn't see very well, and we were clipping right along I guess about 40 miles an hour over the whole desert earth and all of a sudden we came to a real deep break off of the earth. It seemed like thewhole earth just opened up and they looked down and finally stopped and looked down and we were sent out to explore the new regions for uranium for possibility of uranium and we couldn't fly down in these canyons, so we had to go in by foot and we came upon this big one and it took us six hours the next morning to get down inside ofthis big chasm. It was, I guess it was two hundred feet wide, fifteen hundred feet deep and it ran for about, oh, five milesr.ight down into one of the rivers over there. So we went down in there on rope and things and got down into one of the formationsthat lay down in the bottom of that country and sure enough we founda vein of uranium about six inches thick and the vein I guess was about fifteen feet long and we brought samples back up with us and by the way,it took us a full day to get back out where we came from and we showed it to our geologist and he told us that it was a very10
 A: good show of uranium but it wasn't very feasible in the areathat it was in. It would be too costly to get the stuff outSo, it was quite interesting to work in that area and find the different formations that contained this uranium, but it wasall, as far as I know, it was secondary uranium. It wasn'tthe prime or the mother lode that everyone was always searching for. I know there was a lot of people that spent a lot of money in that country and some of them made a lot of money and some of them spent a lot of money and never did do any good and youcould walk through that area up there and have a real good showing on your geiger counter and you'd start your tunnel to dig for it, and you might go in ten feet and that would be it. I saw a man once find a whole tree that was just a real high grade uranium.It came like black powder, a real soft like pepper for instance, the tree impregnated in the standstone was about two foot in thinkness and the branches went off, I would say maybe ten feetin each direction. So, he blasted that thing out of there and gotsixty-five hundred dollars for this tree that was forty feet long. Then, when the tree was depleted, then that was the end of the uranium ore. It was real, like I said earlier, I couldn't figure out why the uranium deposited in those trees. Geologists could tell us but I don't understand that. It made a lot of people really disappointed when they would find these old fossilizedthings and dig them up and then that would be the end of the uranium. Of course, there were other formations that contained
 A:R:A:high grade pitch blend and uranium that wasn't in quite such confined area and they're still working those mines up there now.Did your father have a sixth sense of location of uranium?Well, like I said, he was a self made geologist. You take twenty-five years of worki.ng in the earth and different mines and things like that and you kind of really know. But I do feel he had a sixth sense. Usually, when he set out to do something it would be right, and I'm sure that, and well, hehad further proved his knowledge to be right on the primary uranium ore by the geologist that he came in contact with. They told him that he was right in his ideas there.When he sold stock in his corporation was it so that he could advance his prospecting claim? 'Yes, yes, he needed money. He would sell stock in the corporation.Did you keep it just to the immediate family or was it open to all the public?It was open to all the public yes. We came from Manti, a little town of Manti, and of course we sold our first stock to thosepeople that were sincere to what we thought we had in the little country town first, but from then on it was people who had money that wanted • • •R:A:R:A:12
 R:A:You mentioned the Californians were a good source of revenue.Who was promoting this sort of speculation on their part? Was itpeople like your father or was it a big corporation behind these promotions?No, it was small promoters that heard about the uranium boom in Utah. Anytime you have a boom like that and I suppose it's thesame during the gold rush time, you'll find promoters that like to go out and sell land for investment and especially uranium becauseit was red not in the '50s and people heard that there was a uranium boom in Arizona and Utah and especially on the Colorado Plateau.Boy, they wanted it, because they heard that old Charley Steen and Pick hitting it by the millions of dollars, but it was private people, private promoters. They contacted my father because they heard he did this type of work you know, fly the country and stake claims. There, boy, at one time I think he had on his desk well over a hundred people that wanted to buy anything that he could stake with any kind of a count at all, just a flicker of the needle on the geiger counter. That's all, and you could sell it for alegitimate price.Was this government regulated at all?Well, from what I remember, all you have to do was go up thereand stake a claim and get the claim papers into the courthouse ofthat county and we had to do, and by the way, on those claims that we staked which there were about twelve hundred claims • • •R:A:3
   R:A:This is in the thirteen miles?Yes, on those claims we had to do,I think it was hundred dollars worth of assessment work on each claim per year so that took a lotof money right there to even keep these claims in order from yearto year until you got the exploration taken care of. But the questionwhether the government--I really don't know. All I know is thatit was open for anybody who wanted to stake claims. Now, while wewere out there staking claims it might be interesting to tellyou at this time that anytime you have big money building in any area or people lurking around here and there trying to find the claim, you'll find what we call claim jumpers and those claim jumpers were--there were quite a lot of claim jumpers in that area and it brought back the old West it seemed to me like. In the fifties it was just like in the old West when they found the gold, the mother lode gold country in California. Claim jumpers wentin there by the thousands to try and finagle somebody out of their claim and the way they did it with us--I know three of the men that actually did that for a living and they were mean people and the law in that country was that you could wear your own gun justlike you did back in the early old days and we did. I just had a 22 and my brother had the same. If nothing else it might scare somebody off of your property, but these people come right out onour property and a law states that if you have claims running for thirteen miles and three miles wide, that a man can go in there,14
 A:and for instance, if I would have taped it off or walked it off like so many people do--but if I would have overstepped it andif I would have gone over fifteen hundred and five feet, instead of fifteen hundred feet and I would have written down on myclaim papers that I went fifteen hundred feet this man could have shot in with a transit to get a legitimate difference, and if there had been, if I had been over, he'd come in with a pie shaped little claim, five feet wide and six hundred feet long and that's what they were doing in that country and he could have staked that claim and if we would have sold out to some big company or big corporation for x amount of dollars, we would have first had to pay him off to get him out of the way, you see, this claim jumper. But, luckily, my father had the insight to go ahead and have it done, and we went to school instead before we started staking claims and we did it all with instruments and then we made each claim just a little bit shorter than it should be and not over.So our claims are all in one package and no one could get in, but our neighbors were not so fortunate. They went out there and stepped it off, you know every second step equals five feet, maybe.Maybe!So, they went ahead and stepped it off and they were over and these three men come in and they staked a claim right in the center of it,and they had a chance to sell their group I think of about eighteen or twenty claims, I forget now, but they wanted to sell it, but the claim jumpers wouldn't let them sell until they were paid off. SoR:A:5
 A:R:A:there were these people to contend with up there and it happened quite frequently.Did you have a lot of deal~ngs with the larger uranium companies?Of course, myself, I didn't. My father may have done, but we visited their mines once in a while. There was Vanadium Corpor- ation of America and the Atomic Energy Commission, and of course, Pick and Steen. I visited both of his mines and they were multi- million dollar operations and that's all. Just to visit was all that I remember.Were their techniques a lot more advanced than say, your father's?Well, let's say they had more to dig for, so they had real nice machinery and instead of running one or two tunnels, they would go in and open pit mine a lot of their stuff and then they would have more tunnels leading off in different directions, running more crews to take care of the operations.At that time, did you have any type of safety standard that you had to follow in mining?No, I don't think so. Oh well, I take that back. Yes, every miner had to wear his hard hat, of course, and about as far as any other inspections and th~ngs like that, I think it's too early for thepeople to really ~igure this out in the early 50s.R:A:R:A:16
 R:A:Did you know Mr. Steen and Mr. Pick personally?I met, my father had a business meeting with Mr. Steen, and he was from Moab, and he had his operations in Moab and we flew overto Moab one day in a small plane and I think it was a sale of some mining equipment, and I remember walking in there and looking on his desk and he had a pair of his boots that he had worn when hefound his claim and they were on his desk and he had them gold-plated.Gold-plated!And the holes were still on the bottom and the side of the bootsand there he sat. He didn't look like a rich man but things were really buzzing around that office and in the town of Moab. Itlooked like Freemont Street in Las yegas, it was so busy in the 50s. It was hundreds of people there and they were from all different states and they were after that uranium, and he had temporary offices right in the city of Moab and that was after, of course, he hadfound millions of dollars worth of uranium ore, but as far as deal- ing with him any more or Mr. Pick, I never did.Did you enjoy your uranium experiences?Well, of course, at the age of sixteen when you have to go out into the desert fifty miles from any town, a young man like that don't really like to do it and I had to stay out there for sometimes twoor three weeks. In fact, I remember one time my brother and myself were out there in that area working and we'd been out there about,R:A:R:A:1.7
    A:oh, three or four weeks, I suppose and we were kind of itchingto go home for a spell. So my father would take one of his cater- pillars and he would swath all the cedar trees off the top of this one plateau and it was only I think five or six hundred feet long and he would land his airplane there, and he was okay as long as the wind was blowing in the right direction, but watch out whenit wasn't. So he flew over one day and checked things out and mybrother and myself told him that we had to get back into town. So, he lit on the small runway and the wind was blowing in the opposite direc.tion, and he could only take off one way and that was downoff the top of the plateau and across the ravine, and if he was lucky his wheels would come off the ground about the same time that the plateau ended and the chasm below started. ·This is a two placed airplane, good for about 500 pounds but we couldn't decide whichbrother should go to town so my dad said, 'Take all your clothes offand all your boots, your hard hat and you can't take any suitcases ·with you. We'll empty as much material as we can off ourselves and we'll try and get off.' So, we ho~ped in the plane, and hetook off and started down the runway and like I said, he had a tail wind and· that didn't help. You should take off in the wind and then we was rumbli.ng down and boy, our hearts were beati.nghard and we were really scared, and finally we got right to the end of where the plateau dropped off and we dropped off right with it and went right down to the bottom of the ravine about a hundred and fifty feet and we was heading for the·other side and he just turned18
 A:the plane to the right and flew down the chasm a hundred yardsand finally got enough altitude and wind to bring us up againoff the top and we made it back in to town. But, to answer your question whether we liked it or not, yes, I believe that it wasone of the most fabulous things that ever happened to me becauseit was out in the wild country and there was a possibility of really making a lot of money. It was just reasons of dollars if you were working in that area and there's the local town's people never did taste until those days in the early 50s. I remember one Sunday we were up in the mines and I found an old twig that exposed itself after one blast off the face and it was on a Sunday and everybody else quit work and my brother and myself went up there and we had an old coffee pot that held about a gallon and we set there picking that stuff up, this powdery black uranium andputting it in this coffee pot and then the next week that wetook our ore into Salt Lake, we got eighty dollars with justthat one little pot. Eighty dollars in the 50s is like a hundred and sixty today and for a couple of sixteen year old kids thatwas a lot of money just working with teaspoons in the mine.My goodness.So, there's always the excitement of really striking it rich, and, of course, we worked with some old miners that were called in from the gold mines to work with us at that time and theyhad a lot of stories to tell us and it seemed like the nightsR:A:
    A:R:A:were fresh and clear and you could sleep at night after you worked all day and real interesting. I could probably go aheadand tell you a little bit about our experiences over in Marysvale or would you want?No, I wish you would.Well then, shortly before, you might reverse this tape, but any rate, shortly before that episode in that country and finding the possibility of a mother lode country, we worked in the town of Marysvale, Marysvale, Utah, and all of that ore was kind of different than it was on the Colorado Plateau. It was in aharder rock, a real hard flint rock and they'd worked those mines as gold mines since the early days, and in the 50s, the late 40s and early 50s they found uranium right along side of what thegold was and so they re-opened up all those mines in that areaand that is what really got us, I guess, interested in uranium,is working in those mines as the driller. In other words, my father was in the well drilling business so he was in that country to drill, not only test holes, but to find where the uranium veinswere, but air holes in the mines. Now in those old gold mines they'll go back in the holes for, or in the mountain side for oh, three or four, five thousand feet in all directions, going up, down, across and around inside the mountain and after they opened them up, after they found uranium and opened them up again theywould blast off a face and it took about eight to twelve hours for20
 A:that smoke and the poisonous gas from the blast to clear out before they would go up there and muck it out, and so they needed air holes drilled in there from the top of the mountain. So we had a transit man, a surveyor,go in there and he would survey theinside of the mine and take all the angles that were necessary to figure this thing and he would go right up on top of the mountain and figure out exactly where our drilling machines should be located up on the mountain so we could drill a hole straight down and intersect their tunnel on the bottom. So the man told uswhere to go and we would take our bulldozers up there and drill it out and clear the road and find a spot and we would pull our drill- ing machine up there and then we would drill straight down, oh sometimes we would only have to go maybe five hundred feet and other times we would have to go maybe fifteen hundred feet. It was real interesting cause we would go down inside the mine and stayback maybe a couple of hundred feet from where the hole should be about the time we felt that we should intercept the tunnel and you could hear it pounding all around us. It was a cable trio outfit and you could hear the hole and the pounding of the heavy toolsall around us but we couldn't tell exactly where it was to the right or to the left, overhead or what and all of a sudden therewould be a big cave-in down the mine about two hundred feet and sure enough we would intercept this tunnel and we would walk over there, look straight up for a thousand feet and you would just see a speck of light and that would be our equipment up on top of the
     A:R:A:mountain and then after putting in the air holes they would open up these old mines and they would operate around the clock you see, because they could get the poison gas out of there.That would take twelve hours?Instead of, well, no they didn't_go in there and shoot twoblasts off a day in an eight hour period. So that would be six operations in one day instead of just one. So they helped outthe situation there, and there was a Lane Burdelson who ownedmost of that mining country up around Marysv_ale and his daught'eris Marie Windsor, the movie star. She may be a little too oldfor you people in college to remember but I, we was up there drill- ing some test holes and she came up and introduced herself and was quite inquisitive about the · operation there, but her father, likeI said, was quite a wealthy man because he used to work in thegold mines and then when they found uranium he just continued andhe knew exactly where to go for it. Through his operations in that area he became a real wealthy man. But, you can go back toMarysvale even today up around the Big Rock Candy Mountain and down towards Marysvale you could see all these roads that are clearedoff by catepillars and diesels and mining equipment trying tofind this uranium and I'd say about twenty per cent of those roads that you would see from Marysvale was made specifically for ourdrilling machines, to drill down into those mines622
 R:A:Was it really kind of different for gold miners to b come uranium miners?Yes, it was the same operation. Instead of looking for gold,he was looking for uranium with a geiger counter and the interest- ing thing that I found looking for that uranium in not only Marys-vale but the Colorado Plateau area is that it fluoreses and witha fluorescent light you can walk into an area and if you feelthere might be uranium and if you get a fluorescent colorationfrom the surrounding rocks there is a possibility there's uranium because some of the uranium ores will fluoresce a bright--just like a fluorescent paint when you put a fluorescent light on. We used to walk in our mines on the Colorado Plateau and shine this light on there and it would light up like a big neon sign so full ofuranium and for exploration purposes the black light or fluorescent light was equally as popular as the geiger counter or nucleometer.We used to drill test holes down at Zion Park. There were someold test holes for gold that some people made about 50 years before the fifties, and we were called in that country to reopen those exploration holes up with our drilling equipment and for theAtomic Energy Commission to explore for uranium and they did andI don't think they found too much. It was a small count but they flew a scintillator or nucleometer out from New York and this one instrument was worth ten thousand dollars. It was real sensitiveand these holes were about four hundred feet deep and they would drop a probe right down inside of it and they would get a count of uranium. But, boy in the fifties, the early fifties, if you2
     A:had any kind of count on your geiger counter at all you couldsell it for, the claim that you claimed, you could sell it. It would depend on bhe man that you wanted to sell it to for the amount, but legitimately, a claim--I think my father was getting, oh, two hundred dollars, two hundred dollars to a thousanddollars for a claim. Some of them that he sold he wished henever would have sold because some of them were real good andsome people made a lot of money on the claim that he did sell to these people and others just bought it for an investment andnever did even go and see the property. It all happened through the mail. I remember the time in the early fifties that you wouldwalk up there on the Colorado Plateau in our area and it would just like--if you looked over the land you could see all these claims. It looked like a graveyard, all these claims and all these monuments that they had up there by the thousands. In fact, there's some of that area you couldn't even stake a claim even if you wanted to because it had been staked by so many people.Were there a lot of claim fueds at that time?Yes, uh huh, yah, you'd hear in the paper all the time--fact there was killings up in that area of people shooting each other and because, especially those claim jumpers. They'd go up and cause a lot of litigation and we felt lit_igation in our own company and corporation with the people we chose to work with us. Now, we found a man once walki_ng right behind us changing the markers in the can to read his name and we had to go through three or four hundredR:A:24
 A:R:A:claims and erase his name and put it in the right name, le Madre Corporation. So, it was like the old West really brought back to life during those times, like the gold rush. It was just like it.Were the people who were discovering uranium, that were actually completely unqualified to be discovering uranium--that it was happenstance and luck that they found itiWell, yes, it's just luck. A lot of geologists claim that they can go right to the spot where it was, but I seen a lot of these people like you and me go up there with a geiger counter and pick up a trace of uranium and stake it and then open it up and then they would have a big find. Yeah, any novice or anyone that had a geiger counter or a fluorescent light can go up there and find as much as anybody else. I'm not saying that the geologist foundmost of the uranium that was deposited in that country. I don't think so. I think it was by sheer luck and uranium really belongs to those people that went out and searched for it. Like I giveMr. Pick and Mr. Steen great credit for what they did. From what I understand, I think it was Steen that was almost broke. In fact,he was broke. He had to borrow his last stake to go out and search for this uranium and had to borrow that from one of his friends andhe was a man that was just broke and yet he knew that if he stuck long enough with it, he probably come up with something and it was during that time that he did find it, from what I understand that ten to fifteen foot vein in high grade uranium-vanadium, in that country25
   A: and he was a wealthy man overnight and I guess that is why he had those boots on his desk all gold plated. He wanted to let theworld know that he was a poor man at one time.R: Was there a lot of exploration done by fathers and sons?A: Yeah, there was~ Most of it was done by Atomic Energy Commisssion. Others were just like plain owners that bought the delicate instruments to go ahead and search for the stuffe I remember one day, we wouldget the high grade uranium out of our mine and we would stack it ona large table. In one week's time we might get two or three tonsof this high grade material and you could walk around it with the geiger counter and you would have to turn it up to the, I forget what it is now, the highest or lowest read~ng and so it would comple~elyburn your instrument out, it was that hot. I noticed one day fly- ing overhead with an Atomic Energy plane, a two engine, a-big air- plane and it had a scintillator hanging from a cord or rope from the tail of the· plane. I_ guess it was h~ng~ng about a hundred and fifty feet and he would fly up these ravines and across the desert and when he would get count he would do the same thing we had done.He'd throw out these b_ags of powder·and then he would go in andsee what it was all about. He flew over our high grade uraniumthat we had out on the table and we were so secluded in that canyonwith cedar trees and other natural surroundings that he couldn't detect that that was our mine. So he· thought that he really found a strike and he flew that area for about twenty minutes, read~nghis instruments, but I guess he found that it was already staked26
 A: and belonged to and being worked by people and so he just--we never did see him again.R: When you passed out the markers out of the claim and find whatyou call the high count, then you have to go deeper into that area, would you stop first at the claims office to find if it was staked or would you have enough information of the area1A: Well, we did a little of both and we did get smart and like you mentioned, after a while. When we first started this there was hardly any claims out there. We was some of the first that was ever in that country, luckily, and it was too bad that we didn't findthat high grade uranium that Mr. Steen and Mr. Pick found, but at any rate, we would drop these things down and go in and get us some jeeps and things.R: The only way you would know is by the claim markers?A: Oh yeah. Like I say there was very few people out there at that time, so we wouldn't really take the time to go in and find outwhether it's claimed. We knew that it wasn't claimed and even from the air you could see these things cause the airplane doesn't flyvery fast, but two or three years after our operations in that area we would go into the local courthouse and find out that area that we had a count on was actually staked.R: How much was the ore running for at the time you were involved in the uranium business?27
   A: Money wise?R: Yes.A: Of course, it all depends on the count of uranium. I think thevery best uranium that we ever produced was about 1 1/2 or 2 percent uranium and I remember seei_ng some of the checks and things and asking my father and I think it's something like two thousanddollars a ton with some of the better uranium and, of course, secondary ore, we took in into Green River and some of it intoHite, Utah, and we just set aside our carload, a train car and we load that car up and they would ship it in to Salt Lake, and Ithink those cars at that time on secondary uranium ore was bringing in, oh, two or three hundred dollars a ton. But even yet, that was really good money for the effort and the labor it took to get itout. It was real good. It's too bad that the secondary ore hadto deplete in so many cases up there like it did and run out.R: Do you think there's still a lot of uranium to be found there, especially with the mother lode?A: I don't .think they even touched the uranium up there in that country and even big operations that they have and have hade I don't think they"'ve even touched it. Like I say, I think the primary source of this is from those intrusions in the · earth and from what our geologists have told us that uranium could have possibly come outas a gaseous state and deposited · in those different formations in28
 A:those dinosaurs bones and things and to get a gaseous state, ithas to first be heated real hot and come up as a volcanic intrus·onlike what we saw and then be washed out into your different form- ations. So I really believe that you will find the primary lode of ore in that same area that we were staking.You mentioned that you have to do a hundred dollars worth of improvement on a claim to keep that claim. Now how long is that enforced? It certainly couldn't be every year.Yes, I think it's every year. Now from what I understand they changed it in these latter years to read something else, but at the time it was a hundred dollars worth of assessment work on each claim per year, and you had to show that to the necessary people.Were there ways to get around this? Were there legal loopholes that people would take?Well possibly there were, but the way we did it to keep some of our claims up, the smaller lots (I'm not speaking of the thirteenhundred claims because the year hadn't gone up yet, but earlier ones) we would take the caterpillar and take one big swap clear acrosssay, a section of twenty claims and like make a road across these claims and you could claim it as a hundred dollars worth of assess- ment work on each claim, you see. And, of course, a lot of our claims were under production and had mines and work on them and we spent much more than just a hundred dollars a year on them, just byR:A:R:A:working.29
   R:A:All the drilling that you would have to do in the thirteen miles would have been all improvement, considered improvements?Yes, as long as there's contingency to each other, I think you did at that time, that you would do a hundred dollars of assessment work, let's say five hundred dollars worh of assessment work onone claim, as long as it's cont~ngency to the other claim or hooked on to the other claim that it would suffice for all the other claims and that's why I think my father did it that way.Have your brothers been involved in this at all since you left Utah?Not since then, no.Did they leave about the same time you did?Ye_s, they left the same time I did.Can you tell me if there's not as much prospecting--I know p.erhaps now in Utah? Do you think it's more scientific and more under the coordination of l~rge companies?Well, like everyth~ng else it eventually becomes that way. I suppose it's that way now. Like·I say, I kind of left all that knowledgeand wanting to do somethi.ng with it and after my father died, I hadno more interest in that type of thing& Cause I kind of let it go,I can't really answer that question. I'm just_going by what happens in this area. Usually the big people take·it over and the peoplethat have money behind them.R:A:R:A:R:A:30
 R: What were your feelings at that time you were prospecting? What were your inner feelings concerning the actual method ofprospecting, where you found ore? Was this a feeling of elat on for you?A: Well, have you gambled in Las Vegas and won a lot of money? To win something or to find something that you don't really have to work too hard for is one of the greatest feelings in the world,and when we used to prospect that country, I could hardly sleep at night just before we would go out in that weapons carrier,even the jeep or even the airplane. The anticipation of finding some- thing that people were finding all around us was sometimes just too great and I think this is one of the reasons that my father, you know, lost his health, because the anticipation of all of itwas too much. When we would go out to search for this material, this uranium, there's always the feeling that you have when you gamble (if anybody gambles) and finding it is just winning the jack pot. You see it there and you're the first one there andwhen the scintillator or the·geiger counter goes wild,then youknow you found something and you can't wait to tell whoever is in charge of the operation what you found. Sometimes we would go out for weeks on end in searching for this uranium, both in the airplane and in the jeeps, on other vehicles and on foot. We'd go out forweeks at a time and never find anything. Sometimes we would go out and we'd find a real high grade count. These were some of the claims we would sell or keep ourselves and the beautiful thing of
   A:that uranium mining is that there was a lot of copper ore I remember that was with it and a lot of other different metals and things, and when you uncovered this, especially on the surface of the earth out on the open where the sun can get at it, it was just as beautiful as any paint~ng you've ever seen. The coloration was there; there was purples, bright yellows, oranges, any color of the rainbow or any color of the earth was in that metal and fromwhat I understand, uranium is very colorless when it's in its pure form like lead~ Ihe surroundi_ng metals~ that was with the uranium was very colorful and it came in all colors and that's what got a lot ofprospectors off course, is that they thought uranium might be a certain color and that they were told you know, like canary yellow, or some other color and they would look for this color letting some of the other real finds go by if they didn't have the necessary equipment to look for it.It must have been a gratifyi_ng experience for you.When we found it, yah.It was most interesting talking with you concerning this. There'sa lot of information which you've given us for the uranium industry, the people that you knew and the experiences you had while youwere in Utah.I'm sure glad I had the experience. Sometimes I think that maybe I'm kind of lucky that I didn't strike it rich and a man getsR:A:R:A:32
 A: educated on what he has to work for on this earth. I'm afra·dthat if I ever did or had of stuck it rich at the early age of sixteen maybe things wouldn't have turned out like they have forme, but I still look for someone to find it up there and I hope they do .R: I'msure they will."