 MICHAEL BENSON Shiprock, New Mexico Tape No. 9
An interview by Kathy Biel July 30, 1970
American West Center University of Utah Uranium History Series

 Table of Contents
Uranium Mines•. .. .... ... 1 Tribal Council. .... ....... 3 Educational Background. . . . . 5 Problems of Young Navajos • • • 9 Future Employment on Reservation . . . . . 11 Anglo's Attitudes•• ..... • • 13 Exploitation of Navajos. ....... . • 16 Bureau of Indian A ffairs . . • • 19

 :MB .:
KB.: MB:
THIS IS AN INTERVIEW WITH MR. MICHAEL BENSON, A NAVAJO COLLEGE STUDENT AND YOUTH NAVAJO NATIONALIST ORGANIZER. THE INTERVIEW IS BEING DONE FOR THE UNIVERSITY OF UTAH AND CALIFORNIA STATE COLLEGE AT FULLERTON, URANIUM INDUSTRY ORAL HISTORY PROJECT. THE INTERVIEW TOOK PLACE IN MR. BENSON'S HOME IN SHIPROCK, NEW MEXICO, ON JULY 30TH, 1g10. THE INTERVIEWER IS KATHY BIEL.
I don't think we're getting that much for our oil, you know, like that.
Uh huh.
---?--- anything we do on that or the uranium or even the coal. And one things I notices ahout Kerr-Mcgee--you know, that's the one that we lease our oil to--our larid, and I noticed that they had a real high profit one year, you know, on the American or New York Stock Exchange, I don't know which one it was. They had the highest profit. And you know, I didn't--we didn't feel that maybe they got it, but we didn't feel this. And they do a large part of that exploitation for oil around here, around this area.
Uh, doesn't--didn't at one time Kerr-McGee have a Navajo mill out here, too, which processed the uranium ore?
Probably. I don't know ab.out it. See, I don't know that much about it. And I didn't have time to write to you about it. That was what I was going to tell you. There's a friend of mine that's doing research on seeing how much money--how much money we have got from
uranilllll in all this. But, I don't know. To my knowledge, we haven't
KB:
MB.:

 BENSON PAGE 2
got that much money from uranilllll, or have we?
KB.: Yes, quite a hit from the mines at Numb.er One and Number Two Monu-
ments back in the middle fifties. There was a tremendous amount of ore being taken out of there, and at one time, I believe, the Tribal Council was receiving up to sixty-two and a half percent of the royalty and revenue. But you say you don't--you haven't seen any evidence of it here. Could it be that--
MB.: Well, it's maybe before my time, see.
KR: Y eah.
:MB: Mayb.e what I--you know, I've gotten interested in the problems of
the Navajos, and I've been keeping up with what's been happening ever since I could read newspapers and all this. I really haven't 1:ieen hack into it the whole time, you know. Right now I'm worried
that there is a lot of money from ore, but I don't think, you know,
somehow I have a feeling we should be getting more. I've always wanted to look into it, but I haven't looked at it--into the debt, and deb.ts.
K.K: Uh, couldn't it he pos.sibJ.e that the Trib.al Council is in control of this revenue and perhaps it's their fault that you haven't seen any evidence of it being distributed?
MB.: Well--

 BENSON PAGE 3
KB: How do you feel about the Tribal Council in general?
MB: Well, I think I like the idea of the Tribal Council, but I think
there are people in there right now that are very slow, and I--
I really think they're under--they're dominated by the Anglos. They're afraid of th.em, I think. I think ..it'·s ·.about time we-~spoke up. I really don't think that--I really don't think that the Navajos are a free people, you know. We always hear this is in the Const- itution, everytying, but I don't think so. You can just feel it,
you know, that the Anglos are running your lives. They teach down
here, they have a superintendant. Many people, even--I've even heard councilmen s.ay that Mr. Makai is run by his lawyers and they are Anglos. And so, you know, this is my feeling towards the Tribal Counc:i:1--;-- we have -some young-people . coming up that are very much, you know, nationalistic Navajo. They're Navajo Nationalists. And
I hope that they will get into office some day, and I think they'll run it lietter. They way it is right now, I think it's just a puppet government.
KB.: You know, when I speak to miners that are working in the mines now,
or have worked in the mines, I've noticed that none of them are aware that there are any revenues at all that are given to the Tribal Council from these mines. What would you attribute that to?
11It: Well, I guess it's just--I don't know. For a long time I guess we

 BENSON PAGE 4
were so used to having Anglos run everything for us that we ourselves look up to the Anglos also. So it's both ways, you know. That is
what we're fighting, I think, b.ecause I'm reading down there on juvenile delinquency---?---
KB.: Yes, I heard.
MB: Y eah.
KB.: How did the meeting go?
:MB: Well, I think it turned out pretty good. But you take this---?---
too, they're just waiting for the Anglos to do something. And then the Anglos, you know, th.ey're the ones, for instance, that say this
is what we should do. They think they know everything, but they don.,t.
KR: _W_gre _these mep up from Window Rock? MR: Uh~-
KK: From over there?
MR: Yes, they were. This happens every now and then, you know. They
come and they have a task force, sort of like in Washington. Usually, they end up in nothing. But this time I think there was a big
enough. outcry saying that we don't want this--this to turn into
nothing. So maybe something will be done this time. But this is the way I feel about the Tribal Council. I don't think they speak
out enough, or they're not--I don'.t think they're as progressive as

 BENSON P A G E 5
KB,: MB: KB: 1:18.:
KB .: MK:
they should he.
Now I notice you' re going to Wesleyan College. Now which--
Wesleyan University.
Are you going there on a scholarship?
Yes. I'm going there on--it's partly a scholarship from the college and the government. But, no Tribal--
Is that the B.IA one?
No B:IA. I could have gotten it if I applied for it, but I didn't.
I realize that Navajos have a scholarship program, but it is very limited. And I think it's only fourteen hundred dollars right now. And they're not too flexib.le ab.out giving money to you if you go way far away, you know, to some of the better colleges, like Wesleyan,
or Dartmouth-, Harvard, and Indian s.tudents should have the opportunity to go to these colleges, too.
Uh., wh_ere did you receive your education before you went to Wesleyan? Well, I went to BIA hoarding school for a while, then I went to
puhlic schools around here and near the reservation. And when I
was a freshman in St. Michael's Mission School--uh, that's a school
at St. Michael's, you know, near Window Rock. Uh, the nuns filled
out an application for me to go to prep school, and I got scholarships. I went to college prepatory school for three years and from there I
went to W esleyan.
KB..: 118.:

 B'.ENSON
PAGE 6
KB: MB: KB: MB..: KB.: MB: KB: MB.: KB: MB: KB:
MR:
I see. You went to hoarding school. Where was this? A t---?---.
Uh, I'm not familiar with that. Is this--
It 's near--
Near here?
It's up from Two Great Hills.
Oh, yeah.
Do you know·where Two Great Hills is?
Yeah, uh huh.
It's out that way.
Uh huh. What did you think about the education you received from the BIA boarding school?
Well, I can remember, you know, only patches. But I remember--you know, the thing--I'm just a musical nut or, you know, the B.ig Step (?). You know it's been a long time since Navajos weren't allowed to
s.peak Navajo in schools, but I can remember we'd be playing out there, and they'd say don't speak Navajo. I can still remember that. And there was this orientation towards only White boys, so that many of
the kids, I think, that they look down on their own people.
KB.: Now what do you propose--that the Navajo maintain only their culture? MB~: Well, I don't know. I would be--I would attempt to be a lot more
wiser and a lot smarter than I am to say what the Navajo should do.

 BENSON PAGE 7
this or we should do that. I think that we Navajos should be proud of ourselves. And I think that if we go on and do everything being proud that we are Navajos and believing in Navajo power, then I think we'll,--you know, everything will just fall into place. But if we let the Anglos rule over us, then we're not deciding for ourselves what we should do. We're not controlling our own lives. And I think if th.e Navajos. don't control their own lives, there's no--everything can happen, but there will be a continuation of the Navajo people.
I don't think anyone can go wrong in---?---, but there will still he a Navajo way of life. I'm sorry that I can't give you that much infonnation on, you know, the uranium.
KR: That's all right. This is a part and aside from that. And really it's an outcome of it in·a way. I'll work it out. What are you
majoring in .in ~ollege?
MB: I'm not majoring in anything yet. I've just completed my freshman
year.
KB: Uh huh. Do you have any ideas what area you'd like to go into? MB: Uh, I'm thinking of economics or journalism.
KB.: Are you going ·in politics .at all?
MB: Uh, yeah, probably. Not really politics--well politics to me means-- I don't know, I've got a bad idea of politics, you know, when some- body says·politics, but I would like to see some good come to the

 BENSON PAGE 8
Navajos, and anyway I can help do this, I'll do it.
You said you hope that young educated men who are nationalistic would get into Tribal Council positions.
Uh huh.
KB:
I mean there's an age--1 think you have to be thirty before you can
be on the Council. And I think this should be lowered down. To be chairman it's thirty-five. This should be lowered, too, I feel. And I think it will be. There are a couple of councilmen that are pulling for young people, Mr. Bullison (?) and Mr. Dodge. They both mentioned getting young people involved, and I think Mr. Dodge went so far as
to say, ''Yeah, the voting age should be lowered to eighteen years." KB.: I noticed you introduced Mr. Bullison at the Conference.
MB-: Oh, yeah.
KR: What did his speech entail?
MB,: Uh, I wasn't there to listen to it, but I heard it from others that
he talked about the youth involvement. And in the meantime, see, this ---?--- youth in the b.ackground, you know, some graduation that yoμ hear ab.out how w:e're going to be the leaders of tomorrow, but then after that, they forget about it. They don't try to get them involved in the Chapter house(_?), in committees, or, you know, lowering the
MB,:
KB:
MB: Yeah, I wouldn't mind serving in the Council. But there's a voting--
Is this an amb.ition of yours perhaps?

 BENSON PAGE 9
KB.: }1R: KB.: MB.: KB: MB.:
voting age would be a good step since I think a good degree of the Navajo people are under eighteen years or age.
Yes.
B.ut generally, all these movements involve the youth.
Now this is. a conference to help solve some juvenile problems?
Oh, for today, yeah.
Now, what are the main problems as you see them?
Well, I think they're bored. The young people don't have that much to do, you know---?--- facilities, or---?--- and all that. And also, I don't know what it is, maybe many of the--many Navajo kids come from families which are traditional, and they know no other
w.ay of life, but when they come to school, it's different. So they don't know how to entertain themselves in this new way. Before it
was squaw dancing, racing, and all that. Now it's different. Their parents can't really, you know, teach their children. And so--but
what I think they have to do is get the young people involved and serious in some of the working of the Council, the Chapter houses
housing problems. And I think the big summer work programs, not the--you know, clearing away of tumble weeds or scrubbing VHS hospital floors.. We have a project over here where the original school system-- this-----?--- where we want it. We know that parents have complaints,
students have complaints, and we know that the curriculum isn't that

 BENSON PAGE 10
good, and we want to see what we can do about this. And we're going to organize teachers and parents behind us to deal with these. I think this type of summer work is good, and we got this money our- selves. We got ten thousand from the Bureau of Indian Affairs in Washington, and there was no doubt involved or any--and I think that young people can really do a lot. And people just have to realize the power they have.
KB.: Now, I don't think you're so much different from Anglo students, what they're protesting for, in some of that. How do you view the students
who go to college off the reservation and don't come back?
HR: Well, it's very few that don't come back. It's, you know, a big myth
I think somebody built up. Most of the people I know around here, they always come back. Most of the people I went to school with, they--they're coming back.
KR: And do they use their education?
MB_: I think they--where they can, they use it, yes. I don't know who
made up that myth, but you know, I think it's very wrong. The only people that I know that stay in large groups are the people that have been pushed away by relocation and this was deliberate by the BIA.
You find a lot of Navajos in Los Angeles and Denver, and this was a result of relocation, or efforts by the BIA vocational training.
Another thing that, you know, that can really help young people are

 BENSON PAGE 11
the teachers. Probably---?--- lots of---?--- to schools. They give the young people low expectations of th.emselves. You know, with this vocational trainirt3 I think they have this racist attitude that Navajo kids are b.etter at working with their hands than their
minds. There's even a Navajo councilman that said, "Well, I need someb..ody to fix my car.'' So what we're going to have is a Navajo nation of welders and mechanics. I think, you know, especially the way we're emerging to a new level now, I think that in this period
we really need doctors and professional people. We don't need iron
workers or that many welders.
KR: Well, what do you see for the future for employment on the reservation
though? There's not that much industry here.
MB: Uh huh. Well, I don't think--some people have the idea that the
Navajos always have to stay here, sort of swarmed like bees on this little reservation that we have. I can't see why they just can't work outside and then just come back, you know. They can work in
Fannington, Albuquerque and around there. KR: And they'd have their homes here in--
MB! W-ell, they have relatives here, and I don't see how you can ever forget your homeland.
KB.: Your roots would still be here?
.MB.: Yeah. They have this crazy idea about leaving your culture. They

 BENSON PAGE 12
think you lose the right as soon as you step out. I think this is crazy. A lot of people have lived outside the reservation and they still speak Navajo, and they have Navajo ceremonies.
KB: What about this problem down in Gallup? Would you explain a little better about what you were trying to do with the pamphlet---?--- vote?
MB: Yeah. But what are you going to do with this information that I give you?
KB: Now these are going to go down on tapes. They're going to be put in a library at the University of Utah and California State College at Fullerton. Transcripts will be made of the tapes and will be
mailed to you, so that you may edit them in any way you wish before the final transcripts are put in the library in Special Collections. These are to be kept there for any future research or scholarship,
and--
MB: And you're working for the University of Utah? KB: I'm from Cal State, Fullerton.
MB..: Uh huh. Okay. Well, that ceremonial thing--I know my philosophy,
or, I don't know how you'd say it, my explanation of the problems
that the Navajos have. It's just that we--I think the Anglos look down on us for what we are, and the Navajos also look up to the Anglos for what they are, and they're down on themselves. And I think what

 BENSON P A G E 1 3
they have to do is to become really free in their minds from all these b.ad things. ab.out themselves and as heing capable of doing anything
the Anglo does without being an Anglo. You know, t hey can do i t . KB': Uh huh•
MB.: Uh, I've heard my own relatives say that, you know. Once you--if a Navajo wants to, even if he doesn't speak a word of English, he can do a lot of things. He can go into an office yelling in Navajo, and they may not understand, hut they'll get an interpreter if he's Navajo and has conf:iLdenc1.e iti·.--hitrirs.elf.:, Then on the other hand, the Anglos, the reason we're down here is because of the way they treat
us. Over here--if you go over here, most of the Indian nurses that you see are practical nurses. I just asked why aren't they registered nurses. It's because of this racist attitude that we have down at
the s.chool. And then those people that come out of Farmington, and
I don't know, from Gallup prob.ably, but from Farmington--I'm sure
that th.ere' s. a lot of stores and companies that have people swarming to the reservation that go around and pick up debts. And they terrorize the people. They don't do it by themselves. In fact, I
just told ·one off that came over here and I said, "It's degrading and you don't do this to yourselves, so you stay out of our reserv- ation too". And, you know, they look down on us, that's why they
do this. In fact, this guy told roe, "It's your own fault. Your

 BENSON PAGE 14
people don't pay their hills." You know, "your people"--already, they've got the attitude as a whole people. They don't put their men after each other the way they do the Navajos. One--one woman
even came to my grandmother, and took a knife, and you know, I don't know what you call them in English, they're sort of pins that you s.ew·on. And she took a knife, you know, and cut them off. And you know·, that's awful. My Grandmother had a lot of dignity and other Navajos respect her. And here this dumb Anglo comes along and cuts them off. If somebody did that to your buttons, you know, you'd feel very low., too. And this is the sort of thing I think we're fighting. And, you know, at the Gallup Ceremonial--what they do there? You know, they have a man inside a little fence like making the sign painting. You know, it's sort of like a zoo. You go to a zoo hecause you see such strange things and you're going to go to s.ee animals. And I th.ink the same ones will really--deep inside
myself I think it shquld be abolished because I think it's just going to--it's unhealthy for the Indian people to--for them to be though.t of as craftsmen and showpieces like that. A long time ago Navajos made rugs, you know. They didn't make them as crafts--arts and crafts. They used it as things they would use every day. And
now a lot of these things that they did as everyday things are looked upon as a novelty, and arts and crafts. I think it's going to have
a had effect, you know, on the minds of the Navajos. I don't even

 BENSON PAGE 15
agree with the heading contest. You know, for Navajos--Navajo girls, they dress up in their outfits. You know, they don't wear it all year round. They· should wear it all year round. They just do it to show themselves off, you know·, as Navajos, or as Indians. And the
Anglos exploit this also, you know, to bring in customers and all this stuff. And this is the way I look at the Ceremonial. I think also the Ceremonial itself, you know, it's an internationally known event, and they call it the greatest tribute which America has to the Indian people, or something like that. And---?~-- a blanket they hide under. For four days, you know, they pay this tribute to
what? They gave us what we call a tribute to the Indian people, and the rest of the time they throw Indians in unsanitary jails, lot of them, you know, are thrown in jail, and they have no alcoholic rehab- ilitation program in Gallup. And yet Gallup makes millions of dollars
off the Indian every year, off Navajos especially. And there's very little support that they give to the Indians Senate that's there. In fact,·-.the United Fund, you know, which comes from merchants, and all that, have cut its funding to the Indian Senate because of what we
did, and all we did was run off some of those leaflets that we handed out last year. And so, a lot of people told us that, you know, from the inside they tell us that this is the reason why the funds were cut off. I think it's not only one specific problem or one person that we're fighting, it's an attitude that Navajos have of themselves
and of Anglos and the attitude that the Anglos have of themselves, and

 BENSON PAGE 16
of Anglos and the attitude that t he Angl os have of themselves , and
of us. It's the whole atmosphere that has to be broken. That's
why I really b.elieve in this Navajo nationalism. And I think it should serve itself in any possible--down from, you know, the old people to the youngest people. All Navajos should be brought up speaking Navajo. And, in fact, I think the Navajo flag should fly
side by side with the United States flag because we hear, you know, that we're a nation within a nation. And this is tr,ue. We're not really Americans.• We don't have the same attitudes or anything like that. But there's a--I don't know if you read the Navajo Times, but there was that letter to the editor today, the first one, and I think that's the type of attitude we need. I think one says that the person that wrote it is an ex-veteran--or a veteran from Vietnam. But he says, "Next time I'm going to fight on my own ground, and I can see
it coming that we'll be fighting with the Anglos again." Maybe the-- I think that he's got the right feeling, I don't--you know, I can't agree with--I don't know whether--well, I can't predict another war as he has with the Anglos, but I think that we're going to have to feel proud of ourselves and we have to feel separate because we are.
KB: About what's down in Gallup--the main thing you're complaining about is the financial exploitation of these ceremonials. You don't want to do away with them altogether, do you? Isn't this part of your

  BENSON PAGE 17
cultural heritage and shouldn't you he proud of your--the art and
crafts that your people have developed? MR: Well--
KB,: I mean, isn't it---isn't it like going into a museum?
MB.: Well, uh, yea, it is like that. You know, it's a distortion is what
it is. It just gives the Anglo people an idea of us that we aren't equal to them when they go and see us at that Ceremonial there. Somehow--T can't put it into words right now, but, you know, the
whole thing is just sick, I think, and it's a distortion of the way things really are. Like there was one idiot at a--you know there's a store along the road to Albequerque from Gallup. He says, "I want
people to know about your culture, and I--" He had a sign that said, "See Indian Squaw Weaving Rug", or something like that. And, you
know, we objected to that. You know, it's stupid, and it's somehow degrading, and we objected to that. And he said, "Well, I want to s.ave your culture." He can't save it. Or, you know, how does he know the culture is dying? What is there to save? Maybe it's just con- tinuing on to a new stage. And here's this idiot, you know, that
s.ays he thinks he--how can he save our culture for us? And we heard some people singing out there, you know. They were singing the Plains Song, and we said, "Oh are you saving our culture?" And we
said, "Who are they singing out there, are they other types of

 BENSON PAGE 18
Indians or Navajos.?" They were Navajos. They were even playing songs.. And this was his idea of saving our culture. And I think the ceremonial is dying too. The Anglo is deciding what he is going to say and what he is going to do with our culture. It should be the Indians.
KB: Do you want to shut out the Anglo altogether?
MB.: What do you mean?
KB: Uh, do you want to see an intermingling and a better understanding
between the cultures with a give and take on both sides?
M:B.: That's exactly what I'm talking about. I think, you know, the Anglos
should respect the Indian people instead of setting them up as
novelties and museum pieces.
KB.: You think it's more sentiment than gentiine··_mter.es.t ·.arid,·.oonc~eIJil?
MB-: Yes. I think it's--well, there's--you know, these Anglos are good at it. They talk of brotherhood and equality. These words come easy for them, but they don't follow them. And this is what I think the problem is. It's the whole atmosphere.
KB~: Then w.hat you're saying is that it's the discrepancy between the four days of the ceremonial at Gallup and then all the other days of the year--the treatment that's accorded to the Indians?
.MB-: Yeah, yeah, that's exactly what I mean. The distortion, you know, it's like the way I describ.ed. When I was on the stand with it--

 BENSON PAGE 19
it's the symbol of hypocracy. For four days, you know, they pretent that they are interested in a sick way, and then for the rest of the, you know, the three hundred sixty-five days, they exploit the Indian. And they give very little fiack in the way of public services. Now the Anglos, they do this among themselves, when they have good cust- omers, they do something in return for them. You see very little of
this here at Gallup.
KB,: Do you want the B.IA to leave the reservation, or do you want more
from the BIA or the federal government?
MB.: Well, I think the--I think the federal government owes us a lot. KB: What would you want from them?
MB: Well, I think money without their--you know, right when they give
us money now, they send it direct to an Anglo director, or somehow the Anglo director is an Indian. And even President Nixon has--I don't know if he's sincere about it, but he just made a statement recently.
KR: Uh_huh
:MR: But I don't know. I'm not sure about the BIA. I have a feeling that
if they do away with the Bia, they'll also do away with tribal
sovereignty and all that.
KB.: You think it's that closely inter--
MR: Yeah.
KB: -meshed?

 B.ENSON
PAGE 20
118.: A lot of other people feel that way too. And it's sort of dependent. I would like to s·ee th.e B.IA done away with and sort of have the
funding go to trihal governments· in a way foreign aid or something--
in the way that is done.
KR: Now this hrings me hack to the revenue and the royalty. I've read
that these royalties and the revenue had made the Tribal Council more autonomous. Do you believe, that's true? They have money, but only have--power--
MB..: Yeah., you might say that it has.
KB.: They're not as dependent on financial aid from--
MR: Yeah, hut you still can't overlook the fact that even the Tribal
Council usually ends up---?--- Until only recently they have spoken up. They always used to have an Anglo at the top. But now, you know, like they would find a new---?--- a---?--- for a new police superintendant. And he would really look around hard for a Navajo. They returned the first nominations because there was no Navajo in there. Finally, they picked a Navajo, and I think we're
on the right track now.
KK: How do you feel about the recent appointment of Maurice McCabe for
the Navajo office of Economic Opportunity in the Tribal Council? MK: Oh, yeah, Maurice McCabe.
KK: Now, he's the old treasurer.

 BENSON ,PAGE 21
}IB..: Well, yeah, I don't know Mr. McCahe or I don't know ahout his phil- os.ophy, or his politics, his life, so I can't say. But he's a Navajo, and he was a Navajo the day hefore, and just that fact is good.
KB.: Well, it is said that h.e was in opposition to .:..--?--- in both elect- ions·.
:t1B.: Oh yeah, I read that too. Well, I said that I don't know that much abnut Mr. Maurice McCabe, so I can't say anything. I read the article today too.
KB.: I see. Well.. I want to thank you for taking time out to talk to me and- -
